<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicus absolutus adespotos the compleat physitian, qualified and dignified : the rise and progress of physick, historically, chronologically, and philosophically illustrated : physitians of different sects and judgements, charactered and distinguished : the abuse of medicines, imposture of empericks, and illegal practisers detected : cautioning the diseased in the use of medicines, and informing them in the choice of a good physitian / by Everard Maynwaring ...</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32063</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12309518</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12309518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59336</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59336)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1016:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicus absolutus adespotos the compleat physitian, qualified and dignified : the rise and progress of physick, historically, chronologically, and philosophically illustrated : physitians of different sects and judgements, charactered and distinguished : the abuse of medicines, imposture of empericks, and illegal practisers detected : cautioning the diseased in the use of medicines, and informing them in the choice of a good physitian / by Everard Maynwaring ...</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23], 169, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Third word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [4] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <date>February 27. 1667/8.</date>
               <signed>ROGER L'ESTRANGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicus Abſolutus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The Compleat Phyſitian, <hi>Qualified and Dignified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Riſe and Progreſs of PHYSICK, <hi>Hiſtorically, Chronologically, and Philoſophically</hi> Illuſtrated.</p>
            <p>Phyſitians of different Sects and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, charactered and diſtinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>The Abuſe of Medicines; Impoſture of Empericks, and illegal Practiſers detected.</p>
            <p>Cautioning the diſeaſed, in the uſe of Medicines; and informing them in the Choice of a good Phyſitian</p>
            <p>By EVERARD MAYNWARING Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Hypoc.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Bookſellers, 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Clariſsimis</hi> D. Dom. DOCTORIBUS <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Scientiſſimis nec non in Arte Medica Nobiliſſima</hi> Eximiis Profeſſoribus, omnibus Hermeticam, <hi>Hypocraticam, Helmontianam</hi> Doctrinam <hi>Candide Profitentibus</hi> ET <hi>Subtiliſsime dijudicantibus SALUIEM.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NE cui veſtrum ſit mirum (viri perquam eruditi, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meque colendi) quod vos, quam-plurimis &amp; gravioribus ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitos negotiis, hiſce meis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellem. Meis dixi imo veſtris: excuſatum me proin habebitis; omnium quippe <hi>familiae Eſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapideae</hi> res medica magni refert.
<pb facs="tcp:59336:3"/>Quod cum ita ſit, rem totam <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> concinnare &amp; veſtrae cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurae ſubjicere decreverim: &amp; ut ſpecimen inſequentis operis ante omnes quoſcunque habeatis; offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium meum duxi, hanc <hi>ichnogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> delineatam primo vobis offerre.</p>
            <p>De artis noſtrae dignitate &amp; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate vobis dicere, prorſus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervacaneum eſſe autumo, cum vis ejus admirabilis apud nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem veſtri lateat; &amp; major eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> excellentia, quam ut ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus meus ſit ejus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde haec <hi>Sicco</hi> (quod aiunt) <hi>pede praetereo.</hi> Verumenimvero de me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinae ſcelerato abuſu &amp; inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um medicorum contemptu indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no (quae doleo) dicturus ſum vobis. Nil eſt in rerum natura tam excellens &amp; laudabile, nil tam utile &amp; neceſſarium, quod
<pb facs="tcp:59336:3"/>non abuſu in contemptum &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum perniciem abeat: &amp; ita re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vera prae ſe gerit praeſentis ſaeculi conditio, quod omnes infimae ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis homunciones paritatem cum medicis ſaltem jactant; &amp; cuique ſe medicum profitenti ſtatim cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur: praeſtigias proin horum <hi>pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do-medicorum</hi> &amp; impoſturas, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus credulum vulgus quotidie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcant, pateſcere operae-praetium duxi; magnum ut populus ſciat diſcrimen <hi>doctum indoctumque</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe medicum. Porro autem, <hi>Empericos, Agrammatos</hi> &amp; id genus <hi>medicaſtrorum,</hi> quod attinet; qui legem <hi>Hypocraticam</hi> violare &amp; in <hi>nobiliſſimam hanc artem,</hi> inique ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repere non ſint veriti; qui mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bos judicandi juxta artis praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſcientiam non ſint adepti, at titulum &amp; perſonam <hi>medici</hi> ſibi vendicant: homines iſtiuſmodi
<pb facs="tcp:59336:4"/>audaces ab exercitio medico pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribere aequiſſimum autumo; eo quod medicina non uti ſed abuti tantum norint, &amp; temerario au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu indies experimenta per mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes agant; ut cum <hi>Langio</hi> medico illo celeberrimo dicere auſim; <hi>plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Empericorum temeritate, quam morbo aut hoſtis gladio interimi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Antiquorum <hi>ichnobatos</hi> quod ſpectat, quorum ſervilia ingenia auctoritati nimis addicta, omnia <hi>Scholae Galenicae Dogmata</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitioſe colunt; nemo aegre ferat, cum redarguantur, nec odio me habeant reprehenſorem, ſeipſos autem ſeductos ac errorum reos incuſent; proin &amp; à veritate, non à ſcriptore caſtigari putent: quandoquidem nihil per invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, aut aemulationem, nec ad aucupandum gloriam dixi; ſed
<pb facs="tcp:59336:4"/>veritatis Zelo, <hi>Medicinae Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atricae &amp; Chymiatrorum amore</hi> plenus; <hi>hoſtium eorum</hi> ſtudia &amp; traditiones <hi>Sine Theta praeterire</hi> non potui.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chymiatrum,</hi> ſolertiſſimum il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum naturae Arcana ſcrutato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem quod attinet; qui <hi>medendi artem</hi> inſtaurat &amp; ornat, in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ut <hi>Medici Abſoluti</hi> titulum prae reliquis omnibus ſolum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reatur: non opus eſt hujus glorioſi Laudes prolixius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrare, cum opera ſuae famae perennis per totum terrarum orbem monumenta erexerunt.</p>
            <p>De Medici Officio in <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macia</hi> non nimium ſevere, nec praeter Dignitatem ejus, Statui; ut quiſque ſcilicet more Majorum, praeparatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Medicamentorum <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<pb facs="tcp:59336:5"/>accurate ſit peritus, pariter ac <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pharmacopoeius</hi> valde dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens &amp; expertus; quum in hoc praecipue, tum aegrotantis vita, tum medentis fama maxime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtat. Poſtremo, de <hi>Chymici</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratus praeſtantia &amp; neceſſitate in <hi>arte medendi,</hi> pauca dixi; ut <hi>Chymiae</hi> commodum &amp; excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nulli non in majus innoteſcant.</p>
            <p>Labores hoſce meos quales<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque judicio eruditorum ſubji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio: cum omnibus autem placere &amp; ad cujuſvis guſtum calamum temperare, nemini hactenus acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit, ſed diverſa de ſuis laboribus quisque expertus fuerit judicia; eorum vero quamplurimis, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem egregiis <hi>medicisque abſolutis</hi> hoc opus non ingratum fore valde ſpero: in quantum non meam, at enim <hi>cauſam medicinae,</hi> imo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram <hi>egi.</hi> Si quis verum alius
<pb facs="tcp:59336:5"/>farinae, faſtuoſo ſupercilio ex alto deſpiciens, qui nil niſi ſua ſapiat, haec parvi fecerit; vel privato quodam odio &amp; invidiae ſtimulis actus, de Scriptoris fama inique detraxerit: id non multum cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, nec me hilum commovebunt <hi>Zoilorum</hi> ſibila &amp; morſus; quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe quod hoc genus hominum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viciis tantum quae in fumum abe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, non argumentis pugnare; &amp; <hi>miſo-Chymicos</hi> mihi nihil obeſſe in acutiſlimorum <hi>Philoſophorum</hi> &amp; illuſtrium <hi>Medicorum</hi> favore compertum eſt; nec de jure meo detrahere poſſe, ſat ſcio.</p>
            <p>Haec ſunt <hi>(viri eruditiſſimi, Jatro-Chymici experientiſſimi)</hi> quae ſub examinis incudem (coram vobis) revocanda digna judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi: vos literarum &amp; inclitae me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinae proceres; vos aequi aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matores Scientiſſimos, hac boni
<pb facs="tcp:59336:6"/>conſulere ſpero: conatibusque noſtris in medicine, medicorum, nec non aegrorum gratiam ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aſpirare rogo, caeteros non moror.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Veſtri obſervantiſsimus.</hi>
EVERARDUS MAYNWARING.</signed>
               <dateline>Dat. <hi>Londini</hi> exaedibus meis, <date>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                     <hi>Cal. Martij.</hi> 1667/8.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:6"/>
            <head>TO THE Judicious Reader.</head>
            <p>OF all Arts,
<note place="margin">Hypoc.</note> ſayes <hi>Hypocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> Phyſick is the moſt Noble: but by the ignorance of ſome that profeſs the Exerciſe thereof, and people raſhly judging them to be Phyſitians; it may be thought more inferiour then the reſt.</p>
            <p>The abuſe of this excellent Art being grown ſo common; the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and worthy Profeſſors not ſo highly eſteemed as heretofore, and as they ought, gives me juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to examine into the matter, how this ſhould ariſe, and to vindicate both from Calumny and diſrepute, in demonſtrating and diſcovering to you who is the Phyſitian <hi>quem creavit
<pb facs="tcp:59336:7"/>altiſſimus,</hi> and who they are that ſcandalize this ancient renowned Science, and bring diſrepute upon the true legitimate profeſſors thereof. <hi>Sunt enim Medici nomine multi, re vero perpauci.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe later times more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, practiſers in Phyſick are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed; and if they were men qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and legally inducted, it were well: but to find Mechanicks and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate perſons of all ſorts, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly ignorant, and impudently perſonating the Phyſitian; audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aſſuming and uſurping the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Title, couſening the Sick by a counterfeit Authority; <hi>proh faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus!</hi> that I cannot ſay whether is more mad, the people that countenance and applaud them; or theſe Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſters that delude the people.</p>
            <p>And ſince Phyſitians are not of one ſpecies, but different in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb facs="tcp:59336:7"/>and practice; pretenders alſo to this worthy Profeſſion, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of it, very numerous and of a different extraction I think it worth my labour to give you ſome brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and Character of each; and worth your obſervation to know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and diſcern the one from the other.</p>
            <p>If the axiom be true, that <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſita juxta ſe poſita magis eluceſcunt;</hi> then I have not unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily brought theſe different perſons upon the Stage together, but that they may more eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be diſtinguiſhed and adjudged, which is my preſent purpoſe and deſign.</p>
            <p>Here are both learned and illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: the worthy legitimate Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and a ſpurious Brood of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Medicaſters: here are <hi>Filii
<pb facs="tcp:59336:8"/>Artis,</hi> and here are <hi>Magiſtri Frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis;</hi> Sons of Art and Maſters of Craft: here are Chymical Artiſts, and here are <hi>Vulcans</hi> in Phyſick, they differ in their worth, ſo are they diſtinguiſhed by their Habit: ſome wear the Gown, and dignified with a diſtinguiſhing Title, which Authority hath conferred on their merits; others wear a Cloak for their Knavery, and a Title of their own creation and uſurpation.</p>
            <p>This Manual is a Touch-ſtone whereby you may know the true Phyſitian from the Counterfeit; to diſtinguiſh him that hath been educated from his Youth, in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tongues, Arts and Sciences, to fit and qualifie him for this weighty Employment; from him that hath been trained up in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture, Buying and Selling, or a looſe idle life, no way conducing or
<pb facs="tcp:59336:8"/>fitting him for this grand Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>I have not ſaid any thing here upon the ſcore of Emulation or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to the perſons of any party here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mentioned; but am a Monitor for the good and welfare of this Noble Art, and the Legitimate Profeſſors of it.</p>
            <p>I honour all that wear the Gown in this Faculty, and have a tender regard to their Reputations, and wiſh they were all <hi>Medici Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluti.</hi> I meddle not with men but Opinions and Abuſes in the practice of Phyſick; I aim not to blaſt men, but to reform Errors; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ancient renown and dignity of this Science and the Learned Profeſſors thereof, to that vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reſpect and due acceptation in the world.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding I know I ſhall diſpleaſe many, and contract Envy
<pb facs="tcp:59336:9"/>by this Work, <hi>ut ut ſit, jacta eſt alea;</hi> I ſhall venter that and do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it; <hi>Veritas odium parit.</hi> But I am not diſcouraged in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, <hi>Cauſam Medicine ago;</hi> nor will I ſpare the opinions or practices of men, that tend to the prejudice and diſ-eſteem of this moſt excellent Art, and the Reverend Learned Profeſſors thereof, that in this later Age are induſtrious diſcoverers of Truth and Errors, by Pyroteckni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Experiments and Tryals; and are a Credit and Ornament to the Profeſſion, by their expertneſs in Pharmacy.</p>
            <p>I have impartially given every one their due; and ſet forth each Party by their proper diſtinct Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters: let the world now judge who are <hi>Medici Abſoluti</hi> Compleat Phyſitians qualified and fitted for this great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, founded
<pb facs="tcp:59336:9"/>upon right Principles, laborious Searchers into the Secrets of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reaching forward to advance and approve the excellency of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and who they are that make no Proficiency or Progreſs, by a ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diſquiſition of their own; but in a ſluggiſh acquieſcencie and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous ſatisfaction, live upon the Labours of their Predeceſſors and Patrons, ſet down here as a <hi>Ne plus ultra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may ſee by this Perſpective who are graduated and dignified by Authority in this Faculty, legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and approved, that are to be accounted Phyſitians; men ſet apart from their Youth, deſigned for, and educated in all neceſſary Learning, to accompliſh and fit them for this grand Employment: and who are the rude Invaders of this worthy Profeſſion, fallaciouſly uſurping the
<pb facs="tcp:59336:10"/>Doctoral Title, to the diſhonour of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitys; illegal and illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Practiſers, that defame this profound Science, and abuſe the Bodies and Purſes of thoſe that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily fall into their hands.</p>
            <p>I have impartially and plainly in this following Work, distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed each Party legitimately concerned in the Practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; and alſo ſuch as illegally pretend thereto; that every one may be accounted and eſteemed, according to their Merit: that one may not unjustly live upon the Credit of another, by counterfeit Qualifications, Appellations and Titles; but theſe Vizards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken off, they may appear to be what and who they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and being thus made known to the World, they may have that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance
<pb facs="tcp:59336:10"/>and repute as their worth or demerit ſhall juſtly chalenge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. MAYNWARINGE.</signed>
               <dateline>LONDON, From my Houſe in Clerken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Cloſe. <date>
                     <hi>Febr. 26. 1667/8.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:11"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract.</hi> I. The Antiquity and Dignity of Phyſick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> II. The Riſe and Progreſs of Phyſick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> III. The Sects and different Judgements of Phyſitians.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> IV. The ſeveral Sorts of Chymiſts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> V. The Chymical Emperick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> VI The Practiſing Apothecary.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> VII. The Rigid Galeniſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> VIII. The Galeno-Chymiſt.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59336:11"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> IX. <hi>Medicus Abſolutus;</hi> the Compleat Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Phyſitian.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> X. Whether a Phyſitian ought to make his own Medicines.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> XI. The Excellency of Chymical Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; compared with Galenick Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tract</hi> XII. The Vertues of <hi>Catholick, Specifick</hi> and <hi>Appropriate</hi> Medicines examined; and compared with each other, in their Efficacy, Safety and Certainty of Operation.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="tract">
               <pb facs="tcp:59336:12"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59336:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT</hi> I. THE Antiquity and Dignity OF <hi>PHYSICK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the time when Phyſick firſt began to be in uſe and practice, and who it was that firſt exerciſed this Art, is not ſo clearly determined by ancient Writers, who varying in thier Opinions, I ſhall not poſitively aſſert the time when firſt it began, not the perſon uſing it; but this we may believe upon good grounds, that Phyſick was in uſe ſoon after the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Medicine God created for the uſe of man, as Sacred Writ does teſtifie. <hi>Altiſſimus creavit medicinam de terra,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 38.</note> &amp; vir prudens non abhorrebit illam.</hi> And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59336:13"/>having ſo great an Author to appoint it we need not doubt, nay, who dare que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the excellency of it. <hi>Artis medicae Seminaria Divina ſunt &amp; Deum ipſum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem habent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Noct. Med.</note> ſayes <hi>Freitagius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether <hi>Adam</hi> uſed. Medicine is not recorded, but that he knew the nature of all the Creatures, and therein the medicinal vertues of all things is moſt probable to believe, being comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the perfection of his nature and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite knowledge; and ſince that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine was created for man's infirmities to which he was ſubject after the fall; we may conclude upon very good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the uſe of Medicine was not long after, it being made known unto <hi>Adam</hi> for the relief of mankind in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, to which he was ſubject by his lapſed nature: and that it was in uſe and eſteem amongſt the Patriarchs, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which being propagated and delivered from <hi>Adam</hi> to his poſteritie: from whence ſome are perſwaded, that Phyſitians were not in being before the Sick; nor the Sick before Phyſitians, but both Coaetaneous, had their being in the world together, having ſo neceſſary a relation and dependance one upon the other.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59336:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> when he came to be great and made Ruler over the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he had his domeſtick Phyſitians: and when <hi>Jacob</hi> died, <hi>Joſeph</hi> commanded his <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> to imbalm his Father, and they did ſo, as you may ſee it recorded in the 50 Chapter of <hi>Geneſis.</hi> And in all ages ſince in the moſt knowing parts of the world, it hath been the Cuſtom with Emperours, Kings and Princes, to have Phyſitians attending their perſons, living honourably in the favour of their great Maſters, reſpected in their Courts, and increaſing in wealth.</p>
               <p>That Medicine and Phyſitians have been in eſteem, and accounted a Bleſſing to a People, Sacred Scripture does ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently inform you in ſeveral places: the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> commending and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the Holy Land, reckons up the Commodities of certain Trees, the Fruit whereof was appointed for Food, and the Leaves for Medicine, <hi>Ezekiel Chap.</hi> 47. ſo that Phyſick is a great Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and to be accounted a neceſſary proviſion for a Countrey as well as food: and Phyſitians have been accounted ſo neceſſary, that the People had theſe in great eſteem in all ages, as ſacred and prophane Hiſtory do teſtifie.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59336:14"/>
               <p>Nay, you will find a Precept for it, and that you are commanded ſo to do: honour the Phyſitian with the honour due unto him, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 38. <hi>ſo the Chapter begins, and verſe the</hi> 12. <hi>Then give place to the Phyſitian for the Lord hath created him: Let him not go from thee, for thou hast need of him.</hi> Prophane Hiſtory abundantly furniſheth us with relations and examples of the Preferments, Priviledges, vaſt Rewards, Riches, Fame and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſteem of Phyſitians, but I ſhall paſs that by now.</p>
               <p>The ſtudy of Phyſick hath been of ſuch eſteem, and ſo worthily accounted, that Kings and Princes have delighted in it, and have been diligent ſearchers after Medicines, as credible Authors do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and ſome of their own works do manifeſt the ſame, recorded and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved both for uſe, and patterns to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, for the following ages.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Solomon</hi> that wiſe and wealthy Monarch, was moſt excellent in the knowledge of Phyſick, knowing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all Plants from the Cedar to the Hyſſop, nor was his knowledge bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here; but alſo he knew the nature of all Birds, Beaſts, and Fiſhes, and was the greateſt Phyloſopher after <hi>Adam:</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59336:14"/>had not the works of <hi>Solomon</hi> unhappily been burnt in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by <hi>Nabuſaradan,</hi> as Hiſtorians report, but preſerved for the uſe of ſucceeding generations, our labours now had been leſs, and our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs greater and more frequent. By ſuch Caſualties as theſe, mortality of famous men, and the loſs of their works, all Arts and Learning have had their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings &amp; ſettings; ſometimes ſhining bright and perſpicuous; in the following age under a Cloud perhaps.</p>
               <p>The ingeny and indefatigable labours of ſome induſtrious men promote and advance all Sciences and Arts, ſet up the Lights and Torches of Learning: but by the ſloth and negligence of the following generations; or by ruine and depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Countreys, theſe Lights are extinguiſhed, and the darkneſs of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Ignorance and Barbariſme over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread a Land. Phyſick or the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Medicine, hath had its vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fate in the world, as other parts of Learning have had the like; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times illuſtrious and ſplendid; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof ſometimes men of great Worth and Learning, redeeming it out of the hands of Ignorance and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, and ſome again of mean parts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59336:15"/>empyrical and not induſtrious, leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its Worth and Value: and this I ſhall more properly obſerve in the following Chapter, noting the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of Phyſick, in ſeveral ages to its preſent ſtate in our own days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="tract">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59336:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> II. <hi>The Riſe and Progreſs of Phyſick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE beginning and increaſe of the Art of Phyſick <hi>Rodericus à Caſtro</hi> ſets forth thus: <hi>Concepit medicinam neceſſitas, ſolertia peperit, aluit ratio, promovit uſus,
<note place="margin">Lib. de off, med. polit.</note> lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> demum experientia conſummavit at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutum perfecit:</hi> Neceſſity conceived Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, Ingenuity brought it forth, Reaſon nouriſhed it, Uſe promoted it, &amp; long Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath perfected it. But this rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical account he croſſeth in another place, and aſcribeth the Invention of Phyſick to God himſelf, having ſhewed unto <hi>Adam</hi> the medicinal vertues of all things, that he might declare it to his poſterity: <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Creatorem Deum Optimum Maximum plantarum &amp; caeterarum rerum omnium fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultates Adae primo Proto-plaſto indicaſſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.</note> eique illarum cognitionem infudiſſe arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The excellency and neceſſity of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is ſuch, that the original knowledge of it is not to be imputed to Chance, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, or Caſual Experiments upon neceſſitous occaſions or otherwiſe, though the improvement and progreſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59336:16"/>of Phyſick hath been much of it acquired upon this ſcore, and is daily increaſed after this manner; but the riſe of it is <hi>à diviniore principio,</hi> which <hi>Hypocrates</hi> could acknowledge and does witneſs. <hi>Primi inventores judicaverunt artem dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,
<note place="margin">Lib. de veter. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicie.</note> quae Deo adſcriberetur, quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum etiam eſt receptum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how the Art of Healing was taught and received at firſt, by what Rules or Method of learning, how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated and the primitive knowledge of it continued to their Succeſſors, does not appear upon any Record that I can meet with: but this we may probably believe they were not ſo expert in uſing thoſe wayes and means to preſerve the traditional knowledge from their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors (as we in our dayes and the later times, whereby Learning does accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and increaſe by Reviſings and daily Additions from induſtrious men) that therefore much knowledge did periſh with the perſons dying in thoſe dayes; ſo that this excellent Art was long kept in its Iufancy, had many beginnings and firſt inventions whoſe general ſame was not ſpread in the world for many hundred years, untill the time of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> (<hi>an. mundi</hi> 2242) the Son of <hi>Apollo,</hi> who firſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59336:16"/>ſetled this Art, and modelled it by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, which he delivered to his Sonns <hi>Podalirius</hi> and <hi>Machaon:</hi> and in this I find moſt Writers conſenting, that <hi>Aeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius</hi> firſt gave the Art of Phyſick a great repute, and himſelf became famous thereby.</p>
               <p>Phyſick at firſt was a ſtranger in the world and few that underſtood the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of it; but ſpreading by time, and growing into knowledge, it was much admired and the practiſers thereof ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: when the excellent worth and efficacy of it was diſcovered, all were willing to advance and ſet it forward; the profeſſors thereof highly reverenced and rewarded with large ſtipends from Monarchs and Republicks, and had Statues erected for them in honour of their memory after their death. Emperours, Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in thoſe dayes were not wanting to promote the excellent knowledge of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, by their own ſtudy and exemplary induſtry; and ſome Medicines of their invention were called by their own names which ſtand now upon Record in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of good Credit for theſe many hundred years; amongſt whom were <hi>Gentius</hi> King of <hi>Illyricum, Attalus</hi> King of <hi>Pergamus, Mithridates</hi> King of <hi>Pontus,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59336:17"/>Dionyſius, Conſtantine</hi> the fourth, <hi>Hadrian,</hi> Roman Emperours; <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> King of <hi>Macedonia, Avicen è ſtirpe regia,</hi> who wrote in Arabick ſome Volumes of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; <hi>Evax</hi> an <hi>Arabian King.</hi> In ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, before there was any certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſick, the medicinal vertues of many things were found out by chance; and by obſervation of the brute Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who by a natural inſtinct do avoid thoſe things that are noxious to them, and follow the uſe of what is beneficial to their natures; and when Diſeaſes and Accidents happen to them, they repair to what is helpful, and uſe it by natural inclination and inſtinct, to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Heathens found out many Remedies by Divination and Sooth-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and invocation of Devils: and <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo</hi> reports that among the <hi>Indians</hi> there was a Law,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1.15.</note> that if any perſon had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a Crime, and did not find out ſome medicinal Remedy, he was put to death; but if he did find out ſome ſuch Experiment, he was rewarded and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by their Kings. But chiefly the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were eager in ſeeking after Phyſical Experiments, and improving their Skill in Medicines; and as <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> relates, they brought out their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59336:17"/>and infirm people into the ſtreets and publick places to inquire of thoſe that paſſed by concerning the nature of their Diſeaſe, and the Remedies that might be good for them: and by what means any one was recovered, it was record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their Prieſts, and repoſited in their ſacred places to preſerve the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of it. In like manner the <hi>Grecian</hi> Prieſts did keep their Phyſical Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſecret places of the Temples at <hi>Pergamus</hi> dedicated to <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Aeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius:</hi> and the Prieſts did communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thoſe Secrets to the Sick, who did receive them with great confidence, as coming from the Oracle of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> as <hi>Galen</hi> reports. And <hi>Sabinus</hi> tells us that the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> did expoſe their Sick in publick places to paſſengers, that they might be informed of Remedies againſt their Infirmities; and this Cuſtom was frequent alſo in other Countreys,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Strabo lib.</hi> 16.</note> as <hi>Strabo</hi> notes.</p>
               <p>It was alſo a Cuſtom in ancient times for Phyſitians to make Experiments upon condemned Malefactors, to try ſome Medicines that were dubious or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, for their better information and knowledge; and the Magiſtrate was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to permit it, for the good of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59336:18"/>to promote the Phyſicians Skill, being ſo neceſſary and uſeful continually. The Cuſtom doubtleſs was very lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and we have reaſon to believe this Art hath gained by it, and honeſt mens lives leſs hazarded; thoſe Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being recorded and brought under Rule, for the uſe and ſatisfaction of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, to guide us more certainly in Practice: and if that Cuſtom were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued amongſt us, Phyſitians might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive much advantage by it and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in doubtful Caſes, of which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he cannot ſo well be reſolved, but with ſome hazard to his Patient, and his own Reputation.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> expired, in proceſs of time Phyſick began to decline and loſe its repute it had formerly, by the negligence of the ſucceeding Profeſſors, and by the injury and ruine of time, which ſwallows up the tranſient glory of all ſublunary things.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Hypocrates</hi> of <hi>Cous</hi> coming into the world redeemed this Art out of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Sloth (<hi>an. mundi</hi> 3538. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Computation of ſome) by whoſe excellent parts and great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, Phyſick was reſtored again, cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated and enlarged. This famous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59336:18"/>was deſcended from <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> as ſome affirm; and that the knowledge of Phyſick was accounted ſo ſacred that it might not be revealed and made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but only to the Off-ſpring of <hi>Aeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius:</hi> as <hi>Lacuna</hi> ſaith, <hi>Caeutum enim erat in illa Aeſculapiorum familia, nè quis rationem &amp; induſtriam medendi, poſseſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem planè divinam à Deo ipſis tantum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſam cuiquam communicaret, qui non eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ex eodem genere ortus.</hi> And therefore in thoſe dayes, they called ſuch as were skilful in Phyſick <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Sons of Phyſitians.
<note place="margin">Freitag. noct. mid. Prolegom.</note> And <hi>Freitagius</hi> ſeems to conſent with this Report: <hi>Tradunt</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>Aeſculapium tantum in ſuos poſteros medicinae rationalis Cognitionem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagaſſe uſque ad Hypocratem, qui &amp; ipſus ex Aeſculapiorum familia fuit.</hi> They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> only propagated the knowledge of Phyſick to his own kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red even to <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> who alſo was of the Linage of <hi>Aeſculapius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hypocrates</hi> lived in great eſteem and renown, was ſtiled <hi>Princeps Medicorum, Hypocrates divinus, Senex venerandus,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> hearing of the fame of <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> invites him to come to him, and writes to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Helleſpont</hi> thus: <hi>Hypocratis
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59336:19"/>Medici Choi ab Aeſculapio originem ducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, gloria artis etiam ad me pervenit: dato igitur ipſi auri quantum voluerit &amp; reliqua abundè quibus opus habet, &amp; ipſum ad nos mittito; nam optimatibus Perſarum aequalis erit. Hypocrates</hi> Phyſitian of <hi>Cous</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> the glory of his Art hath come unto me; therefore give unto him as much Gold as he will have, and abundantly what ever elſe he hath occaſion for, and ſend him to us; for he ſhall be equal with the Nobles of <hi>Perſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding this great invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (ſayes my Authour) <hi>Hypocrates</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to go,
<note place="margin">Freitag.</note> ſaying, The King of <hi>Perſia</hi> does not know, that Knowledge is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Gold; and afterwards at his own Charge he ſails to <hi>Abdera</hi> to viſit <hi>Democritus</hi> the Philoſopher; who lay ſick there. Many examples there are in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the ample Rewards, (many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of pounds) large ſtipends, honours &amp; priviledges given to Phyſitians for Cures, by Emperours, Kings &amp; Princes, ſo greatly valued was their skill, as <hi>Pliny, Herodotus, Philippus Commineas,</hi> and others relate; ſo highly hath this Art been eſteemed, and the profeſſors thereof worthily trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But I muſt wave the relation of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59336:19"/>particulars at this time for brevity ſake.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> next flouriſhed <hi>Diocles Cariſtius, Praxagorus, Chryſippus;</hi> and after them <hi>Herophilus</hi> and <hi>Eraſiſtratus:</hi> about this time Phyſick began to be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three parts, in <hi>Diaeteticam, Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maceuticam &amp; Chirurgicam;</hi> Dyet, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines and Chirurgery: thus by degrees the Medicinal Art increaſed, and ſpread in the world; alſo different Sects and Judgements, amongſt the profeſſors did ariſe, concerning which we will inquire in the following Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="tract">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59336:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> III. <hi>Of the Sects, and differents Judgements of Phyſitians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE ſeveral forts of Phyſitians, and Pactiſers of Phyſick, may be reduced to theſe three heads; <hi>Empericks, Methodiſts,</hi> and <hi>Rational:</hi> which laſt may be divided into two ſorts, <hi>Dogmatists</hi> or <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> and <hi>Chymiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Empyrical Sect were of opinion that nothing was required to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſick but Experience:
<note place="margin">Emperical Sect.</note> now Experience may be ſaid to be of three Wayes, or of three Kinds: the firſt is accidental; when any thing happens by Chance, that you did not expect: the ſecond Experience is <hi>Ex propoſito,</hi> when one does purpoſely and deſignedly make a tryal: the third is <hi>Experientia</hi> imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix; when a Phyſitian uſeth or reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe things, which in the like caſes he has found to do good or hurt, and this is that Experience chiefly meant, which conſtituteth that Emperical Art, upon which bottom this Emperical Sect was founded and denominated.</p>
               <p>Thoſe men judged Reaſon uſeleſs in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59336:20"/>their practice, and truſted wholy to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; and therefore did not trouble themſelves about examining of Cauſes, and ſearching into the abſtruſe nature of Diſeaſes and Bodies: but herein differ the Empericks of ancient times, and theſe in our daies; for they profeſs and own nothing but Experience to be their Guide and Maſter, and herein they were ingenious: but our Empericks pretend not only Experience, but great Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, when they are very ignorant in Philoſophy and the Tongues: now the ancient Empericks, and the modern, neither make inſpection into the Diſeaſe it ſelf or the Cauſe, by a rational diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and inveſtigation (being unable ſo to do) but altogether fix their eyes upon the Phaenomena, the external and ſenſible appearances, the ſyndrome and concurrence of Symptomes, which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorically they have noted in the like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and therefore do give the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.</p>
               <p>This Sect in ancient times, flouriſhed chiefly amongſt the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> &amp; as <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> reports, every Diſeaſe almoſt had a particular Phyſitian, ſome were for the Eyes, others for the Teeth, ſome for the Feet, others for the Hand; and ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59336:21"/>each of them applyed themſelves to the Cure of ſome particular part of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Men of note of this Sect were <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, Philinus, Apollonius, Glaucius, Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus, Tarentinus, Menodotus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in proceſs of time finding their blind Experiments to deceive them, which they wholy relyed on, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to eſtabliſh themſelves upon a better foundation and did inquire into Cauſes, and the nature of things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Themiſon Laodicaeus</hi> introduced and was Author of that Sect called the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodiſts;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Methodiſts.</note> who held that the knowledge of Cauſes did not conduce to the Cure; nor had they any conſideration of the Sick, in reſpect of Temperament, Age, Cuſtome, Sex, ſtrength of the Patient, time of the Year, Region, or any thing elſe which a good Phyſitian ought to have, but only looked upon the Diſeaſe in <hi>facto eſſe,</hi> as it appeared by the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks, and from thence only they took their indication for Cure.</p>
               <p>They made their Art very compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and ſhort, and aſſerted againſt <hi>Hypocrates</hi> who pronounced <hi>Vitam bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem &amp; artem longam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aphor.</note> that the Art of Phyſick was neither long not hard; and <hi>Theſſalus</hi> would vainly boaſt and promiſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59336:21"/>to teach it in ſix months, without the aſſiſtance of any other learning. They reduced all Diſeaſes under theſe two Heads, <hi>Aſtriction,</hi> and <hi>Laxity:</hi> for which two general Medicines they appointed, an Aſtringent for Laxity; and a Laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for Aſtriction; and one of theſe was uſed in all Caſes: of this Sect was <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Antipater, Theſſalus, Trallianus</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>The vanity of whoſe Art was ſuch, that I need not uſe any Argument to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute their Opinions.</p>
               <p>I come now to the <hi>Rational Phyſitians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rational Phyſitians.</note> who are the conſiderable Party, that deſerve to be inſiſted upon and rightly underſtood: they were ſtiled Rational Phyſitians, becauſe by a ſtrict ratiotina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they did ſearch into the Cauſes of all things; and were not contented to truſt Experience only for their Rule and Guide (as the Emperical Sect) but did joyn Reaſon with Experience, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and aſcertain the truth of what they did believe: they took Cogniſance of the whole frame of Nature, and dived into the Secrets thereof; they brought under examination the natural action and proprieties of all things; they conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accuratly the Frame of Man's Body,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59336:22"/>in its natural and preternatural ſtate; what was conducing to preſerve him in health, and what would free him from ſickneſs: they took an account of all the preternatural affects, that humane bodies were incident to; how procured, how differenced and diſcerned, and how to be remedied: and this they did eſtabliſh by Rules and Precepts, to conſtitute and ſettle the Medicinal Art upon a hand ſome and certain foundation.</p>
               <p>Theſe Rational Phyſitians though aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all well, and induſtriouſly tending towards one end; yet differed much in their Progreſs and Medicines to attain it, and ſtill continue ſo to this day.</p>
               <p>Of theſe there are two grand diſſenting Parties; <hi>Dogmatiſts</hi> or <hi>Galeniſts;</hi> and <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> or <hi>Hermetic</hi> Phyſitians: they were called <hi>Dogmatiſts</hi> from the many Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that did ariſe amongſt themſelves; and now called <hi>Galeniſts</hi> from <hi>Galen</hi> their great Patron whom they aſſert, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves to be his Diſciples, and own his Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> lived about ſix hundred years after <hi>Hypocrates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galen.</note> and practiſed Phyſick at <hi>Athens, Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was in great fame and ſplendor: he was a very learned man, and intended the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59336:22"/>honour and good of the Profeſſion, as appears by his great labour and pains which he took in writing ſo many Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of Phyſick, and cruſhing the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perical Sect and Methodiſts</hi> that defamed this excellent Art: but for all this, he was not ſo fortunate in his works, as to build the ſtately ſtructure of Phyſick which he had notably framed, upon a right foundation; which cauſed him to accumulate errors, that his volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Writings are of little advantage, except to thoſe who are wary and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, and rightly principl'd, that know how to pick and chuſe; ſuch I ſay may make ſome good uſe of his Works: but they that admire, and read him ſo as to ſwallow all that's preſented, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a perfect Diſciple of his; ſuch ſhall never be excellent in the true knowledge of Phyſick, if they perſiſt. Doubtleſs had this great Phyſitian been acquainted with the diſcoveries in Phyſick, which ſome Phyſitians in theſe dayes are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of; his parts and induſtry were ſuch, he had excelled all before and after him, and <hi>Galen</hi> then would not have been a <hi>Galeniſt</hi> but a <hi>Chymiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not note the failings of this great man, others have ſufficiently done
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59336:23"/>that already; yet many there are that think his Works moſt perfect, at leaſt will have them ſo, <hi>Servilia quorundam recentiorum ingenia ſatis mirari non poſſum,
<note place="margin">Senert. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. ct diſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Chym. cum Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> qui ſcribere auſi ſunt, ſe cum antiquis er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare malle, quam cum recentioribus verum dicere,</hi> ſayes <hi>Sennertus.</hi> So addicted are many, <hi>jurare in verba magiſtri,</hi> they will maintain the Credit of their Patrous right or wrong. But <hi>Julius Scaliger</hi> notes the pertinacious defence of antique Authors, to be very injurious to truth and increaſe of knowledge. <hi>Equidem ſaepenumerò miratus ſum mortalium vel au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciam vel pertinaciam,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Cauſ. Ling. Lat.</hi>
                     </note> qui tuentur erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, quos ii qui commiſerunt, ſi viverent, emendarent.</hi> Many there are who do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly do ſo adore their Patrons that they will maintain ſuch tenents of theirs; as they themſelves, had they been alive now, would have recanted and receded from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sennertus</hi> his Counſel in this caſe is very juſt and moderate, concerning the truth, and the repute of famous antique Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; his words are theſe: <hi>Antiquorum &amp; magnorum virorum ſcripta &amp; inventa magnifaciamus &amp; gratà mente amplecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur:
<note place="margin">Sen. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ. Et diſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Chyn. cum Galea.</note> iis tamen non tam quia antiqua &amp; à magnis profecta, quam quia veritati con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentanea
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59336:23"/>ſunt, fidem habeamus; ſi vero ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando à veritate deflectant, noſtrum eſſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temus; non maledictis eos &amp; convicijs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſere, ſed corrigere &amp; defectus illos ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plere: amicus ſit Hypocrates, amicus Galenus, imo amicus Paracelſus, ſed nullius tanta ſit authoritas ut veritati, quae prae omnibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his amica ſit, praejudicare debet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall now leave <hi>Galen</hi> and his Party; and come to the other diviſion of <hi>Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Phyſitians,</hi> namely the <hi>Chymical</hi> or <hi>Hermetic</hi> Phyſitians: I ſhall not trouble you with the different opinions about Nomenclature and derivation of the word <hi>Chymia</hi> or <hi>Chemia;</hi> nor do I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at this time, to launch forth into the Controverſie between theſe two great Parties, that is a large piece of work; only I ſhall obliquely glance at ſome differences in the Current of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The name of <hi>Chymist</hi> ſounds harſh in ſome mens ears, and they ſuppoſe <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry</hi> to be but a novel invention: as for <hi>Chymiſts</hi> the Artiſts and Profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I ſhall ſpeak of them hereafter; at preſent we will conſider the antiquity and riſe of this Art; the propagation of it by whom; and thirdly the neceſſary uſe and excellency of it.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59336:24"/>
               <p>Concerning the riſe and invention of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> Authors diſagree in this point; but thus much I am convinced of &amp; may ſafely affirm, that <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> bears a very ancient date, and is of long ſtanding in the world: ſome divide <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> into two parts, <hi>Metallurgiam &amp; Chymiatriam;</hi> tranſmutation of Metals, and making of Medicines; and that the firſt gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and detection of the later. For me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallick elaboration and working upon Metals we find the antiquity of that in Sacred Writ; <hi>Tubalcain</hi> was an Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in Braſs and Iron: now Braſs and Iron is not digged out of the earth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat for uſe, but requires fuſion and artificial ſeparation of <hi>heterogeneous</hi> parts, to fit theſe metals for uſe: nor can we think their tryals and skill extended only to theſe two Metals mentioned; but very probably we may believe they did operate and exerciſe their Art in other the more noble Metals and Minerals. Now for the <hi>Chymiatrical</hi> or <hi>Medical</hi> part of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> though I cannot poſitively affirm that it was in uſe then, yet we plainly ſee there was a foundation laid and beginning from hence that we may probably conclude it was not long after, but medicinal Experiments were found
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59336:24"/>out; for by proving and trying of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals many things are found beyond the intention of the Artiſt.</p>
               <p>But for a more plain diſcovery of this Art, and by a more general agreement of Authors; this profound Art is aſcribed to <hi>Hermes Trifmegistus</hi> (therefore called <hi>ars Hermetica</hi>) who lived in the year of the world 2440. contemporary with <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where he exerciſed this Art: and ſome are of opinion that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was skilled in this Art, being bred up in all the learning of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and that by this Art he pulveriſed the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf. But it is not antiquity that proves the excellency of <hi>Chymiſtry;</hi> for as <hi>Sennertus</hi> ſayes, <hi>Licet hodiè primum Chymia inventa eſset; dignitati tamen ejus id nihil detraheret. Sat enim antiquum, quod fat bonum; nihilque invenire eſt quod non aliquando novum fuerit; &amp; multa pro novis habentur, quae ſunt antiquiſſima,</hi> though <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> were but of a late ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that does not derogate from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Art, the beſt of things had a beginning; though we could not be ſo well ſatisfied and aſcertained in it, having not proved and examined it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, being a matter of time which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly diſcovers all things: but <hi>Chymiſtry</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59336:25"/>hath been a ſufficient time in the world, exerciſed by skilful, learned and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, who have left us ſuch infallible teſtimonies and undenyable demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of its admirable worth, together with our own proofs and experiments, which hath put us paſt all doubting, that we are able to ſtop the mouths of all gainſayers) except the ignorant or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious detractors, whom reaſon cannot rule or perſwade.</p>
               <p>But to let paſs the antiquity and riſe of this Art; we will conſider the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs and gradual perfection, as it hath been handed and delivered even to us in theſe dayes, ſucceſſively by men of great note and worth, and the eſteem they had for it, which alone without demonſtration <hi>de factis,</hi> what it can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, is ſufficient to perſwade reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men into the excellency and worth of it. Philoſophers and Phyſitians that have treated of <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> in <hi>Arabick</hi> are, <hi>Geber, Markos, Avicen, Albumazar, Haly, Rhaſis, &amp;c.</hi> In Greek have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Olimpiodorus, Zoſimus, Heliodorus, Dardanus, Democritus,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>In Latine we have a great company that have propagated and illuſtrated this Art, men of great fame and worth: as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59336:25"/>
                  <hi>Raymund Lully, Arnoldus Villanovanus, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Villanovanus, Thomas Aquinas, Joannes de Rupeſciſſa, Paracelſus, Libavius, Valenſis, Maierus, Baſil: Valentinus, Crollius, Querce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, Mylius, Penotus, Sendivogius, Angelus Sala, Faber, Hartman, Schroder, Van Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Glauber,</hi> and <hi>Swelfer</hi> that excellent Phyſitian and Pharmacopaeian, (with many more which I have not named) men of great Learning and Judgement, laborious in <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> by whoſe induſtry in this Art, we have admirable diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries made to us of the myſteries in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not to be unlocked but by the Key of this Art; by which we are eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon principles in Phyſick more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant with Reaſon, and more ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory then the <hi>Galenick Doctrine;</hi> being enabled thereby to prove them by Senſe,
<note n="*" place="margin">A ſenſibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aim cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio reſtra depe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>det, ut jure Plato dixcrit, ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceros mentis internan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tios, coſque appellaverit quaſi ſatel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, &amp; duces ad veritatem compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> which confirms and determines our reaſonings and dubious diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not give you the account and teſtimony of theſe Chymical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors (though the beſt of Phyſitians) to eſtabliſh and confirm you in the right and juſt opinions of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> that it is the only way to attain excelling Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; but you ſhall have the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Galenick</hi> Writers, and thoſe men of note, approved and imitated in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59336:26"/>their practice by the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> of our times.</p>
               <p>The light of <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> hath ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt the darkneſs of error and ignorance; that the moſt are conſtrained to confeſs and acknowledge its excellent worth and uſe, though they be bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon another foundation, I mean <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenick</hi> principles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Freitagius</hi> a <hi>Galeniſt,</hi> yet confeſſeth the goodneſs of <hi>Chymiſtry: Chymia nulli Medicorum ſordere aut in vilipendio eſſe debet, ſed potius ingenioſa Encheria &amp; elegans praeparandorum medicamentorum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic in ſumma lauda ponenda,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Noct. Med. Cap.</hi> 19.</note> utpote quae ſcitu medicis utilis, quod ejus beneficio divinae aliquot compoſitiones &amp; eſſentiae inventae, multiſque balſamis, eximiis liquoribus ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſque, ante noſtram atatem pene ignoratis pharmacopolia noſtra ditata ſunt, quare his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eculis noſtris magno mortalium bono Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia è tenebris revexit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Mercatus</hi> that Learned <hi>Spaniard</hi> an eminent Galenick Writer, ſpeaks the praiſe of Chymical Medicines, and ſhews their efficacy where others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail, <hi>Chymica enim arte ſumma comparatur mixtis tenuitas,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>de recte prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. Iſu. pag.</hi> 193.</note> qua dupliciter malis penitioribus facit, &amp; quia accedit ad imum radiseſque mali, &amp; quia cum toto af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59336:26"/>loco converſatur &amp; miſcetur,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Med. polit. pag.</hi> 19.</note> ut facilè alteret &amp; evincat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Rodericus à Caſtro</hi> though a ſevere <hi>Galenist,</hi> inveighing bitterly againſt <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus,</hi> yet confeſſeth that Chymiſtry affords them a true way of making Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines: <hi>Nec inficias imus quorundam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediorum ritè praeparandorum cam artem rationem nobis ſuppeditare; &amp; qui hoc praeſtat, hunc verum ac induſtrioſum Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam appellamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hear what <hi>Gregory Horſtius</hi> ſayes (a worthy Phyſitian) in commendation of Chymiſtry, and he joyns <hi>Heurnius</hi> and <hi>Mathiolus</hi> conſenting with him. <hi>Encomia Chymiae non opus est ut hic recenſeam, quia verum eſt quod habet alicubi Heurnius: Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitat jam profectò ſine hac arte medicina; quam ab cauſam recte dicit, And:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Horſt. l.</hi> 10. <hi>de pharm.</hi>
                     </note> Mathio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus in Epiſt. Auſim dicere neminem medicum abſolutem eſſe poſſe, imo nec medicorum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, qui in hac nobiliſſima diſtillandi ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia non ſit exercitatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chymiſtry is ſo neceſſary to a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian that he cannot be compleat without it; nay they will not allow him to be an ordinary competent Phyſician if he be not exerciſed and knowing in this Art.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Arniſaeus</hi> Phyſick Profeſſor in the Univerſity of <hi>Julia,</hi> writing to <hi>Horſtius,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59336:27"/>gives him this account: <hi>Studium enim medicum, Dei gratia, viget apud nos, ut vix ante hac: &amp; ne quid deſit, Aperui ſtudioſis medicinae, meo ſumptu, Collegium &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citium medicum, ad quod operas ſuas mihi conduxit Auguſtus Etzlerus, homo indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrius &amp; in artis operibus diu verſatus; Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio &amp; apud vos Chymiam publicè &amp; doceri &amp; exerceri,</hi> To which <hi>Greg. Horſtius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns him this anſwer: <hi>Noſtri quod olim, ubi commilitones eramus in Juli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> veſtra Academia, praeceptores noſtri, Clariſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Dom.
<note place="margin">Horſt. Epiſt.</note> Jacobus Horſtius, patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us meus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norandus, Clariſſ. Parcovius, Arnoldus, Sigfridus &amp; Siddelius, nihil in ſeſe deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari paterentur, quo ſtudioſae juventuti po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terant inſervire, quod corundem monumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſatis confirmant; Unica Chymia deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur—Caeterum conatus tuos laudo, qui nullis ſumptibus parcis, quo ſarta tecta fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatis medicae exiſtimatio nobis maneat; exercitium Chymicum Philiatris aperuiſti non tantum, ſed etiam ejuſmodi collaboran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conduxiſti, qui jamdudum ſua diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia multis innotuit: nos etiam Chymica tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare non ignoras:</hi>—this bears date 1617. you may ſee what eſteem Chymiſtry hath had in ſome Univerſities, the ſtudents inſtructed in it and exerciſed; and thoſe Phyſitians that were not skilled in this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59336:27"/>Art, it was accounted in them a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Belzar</hi> Chief Phyſitian to the <hi>Elector of Saxony,</hi> writes to <hi>Horſtius</hi> that eminent Profeſſor, chiefly to give him this account: <hi>Caeterum quod ſcire geſtis, noſtra officina Aulica remediorum Chymico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum varietate ſatis inſtructa eſt, quorum Catalogum propedièm meus Dominus videbit.</hi> But that which you deſire to know, our Laboratory at Court is ſufficiently fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with variety of Chymical Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, a Catalogue of which, forthwith ſhall be preſented to the Duke. In <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtius</hi> his anſwer to this Letter he writes, <hi>Videant oſores Chymiae, praeter ſpem ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quotidie magis utiliſſimam hanc artem magnatibus commendari</hi>—the haters of Chymiſtry may ſee beyond their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, this moſt profitable Art of Chymiſtry daily to be eſteemed by Nobles.</p>
               <p>Chymiſtry and Chymical Medicines were accounted the glory of a Phyſitian with theſe learned Profeſſors; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it may well be; for by this he is what he is, if he be a Phyſitian of worth; and without it he is of little value, for he can have but little true fundamental knowledge in Phyſick.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59336:28"/>
               <p>Chymiſtry makes a man an exact Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſt; and this is the foundation for a Phyſitian to ſtand upon; and this leads him into the Secrets and Curioſities of Nature which are hid to all thoſe that have not this Key. Here Cauſes and their Effects are diſcovered, and their mutual relations owned: by a Chymical <hi>Analyſis</hi> and unravelling of mixt Bodies, is diſcovered their heterogeneous parts and diſtinct properties; whereby they are ſenſibly manifeſt to be what they are, which before was but dubiouſly diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of at random.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sennertus</hi> a ſolid Writer, generally approved of by all the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in his practice, gives this account of Chymiſtry.
<q>Almoſt all that hath been ſaid by the Chymiſts in the praiſe of Chymiſtry and Chymical Medinines, we freely ſubſcribe to.</q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſ. &amp; diſſ. Chym. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m Gal. cap.</hi> 2.</note> Then he brings in <hi>Schenkius</hi> a <hi>Galeniſt</hi> confeſſing the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable worth of Chymiſtry, and recites his own words which are theſe: <hi>In ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randis mixtis naturis admodum ingenioſa est ars Chymica, ut digna ſit admirationis, &amp; minimè contemnenda &amp; negligenda à Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Meſue</hi> of a toyal bloud, a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian who lived about 500. years ago,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59336:28"/>whoſe works are well eſteemed; ſpeaks thus of Chymical Phyſitians: They are called <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> who make manifeſt and diſcover the hidden properties of things; that I may confidently ſay, ſcarce any one is able to attain to the internal ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe knowledge of things, who is not skilful in Chymical Operations; by which natural bodies are artificially diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and ſevered into parts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antidotar. diſtiect.</hi> 21.</note> from whence the admirable conſent and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of things are diſcovered, which otherwiſe would remain occult.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sennertus</hi> in the ſame Tract mentioned, reckons up more Converts, eminent Phyſitians that began to applaud Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry; and became Diſciples of this profound Art: <hi>Quae cum ita ſe habent, chariſſimi quique medici Chymiam, poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſuperiore ſaeculo inclareſcere coepit, &amp; coluerunt &amp; laudarunt; Langius, Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus, Geſnerus, Crato, Zuingerus, Schen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius, Horat. Augenius, Minadous, &amp; plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimi alij.</hi> And indeed in our times we find moſt of the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> at leaſt the beſt of them, confeſſing and applauding Chymiſtry, though their practice is Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenical.</p>
               <p>Indeed Chymiſtry requires pains and diligence in making various tryals and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59336:29"/>experiments, before a man can obtain a competent knowledge therin; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires neceſſary accommodations for thoſe purpoſes, which is both charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and troubleſome, that many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline it upon this ſcore, which elſe would willingly embrace it: ſome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpare time to proſecute it; others are aſhamed to begin to learn: for ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and impediments as theſe, <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> is laid aſide; the <hi>Galenick</hi> practice is an eaſier life; thoſe which would embrace Chymical truths, cannot or will not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the Chymical labour and exerciſe in this noble Art; but without manual operations, your ſpeculations are unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and your conceptions erroneous conjectures.</p>
               <p>As for the ſtate and condition of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick in our own times, though we have very illuſtrious diſcoveries made to us, ſuch as the former ages never enjoyed, (thanks to profound <hi>Helmont</hi> and ſome others) and we are in a better capacity to advance and eſtabliſh this excellent Art beyond whatever it hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; yet by reaſon of the diſſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Profeſſors, and a rabble of Empericks and illiterate practiſers, that deſtroy both Art and Artiſts, the hopes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59336:29"/>of accompliſhing this excellent work, now languiſheth before our eyes; and we may fear that Phyſitians of the next Generation will be Mechanicks and not Academicks,
<note place="margin">Tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus metus, prudens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitas eſt.</note> if timely prevention do not turn the Current, by an unanimous conſent amongſt the Learned Profeſſors.</p>
               <p>I have now compendiouſly given you an account of the ſeveral <hi>Sects and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgements of Phyſitians,</hi> whereby they have and are diſtinguiſhed into Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, through the whole progreſs of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to our own dayes: our next buſineſs is a more particular and ſtrict inquiry into the qualifications, and actions of Chymical Operations, and others exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the Practice of Phyſick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="tract">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:59336:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> IV. <hi>The ſeveral Sorts of Chymiſts diſtinguiſhed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Find the people either deceiving themſelves, or being deceived with <hi>Chymiſts;</hi> which hath brought a diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute upon the name, that the Chymical Phyſitian ſuffers much by it; eſpecially in the opinion of the unlearned that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well diſtinguiſh.</p>
               <p>There are four ſorts of <hi>Chymical</hi> men, that go under the name of <hi>Chymiſt.</hi> The <hi>Shop Chymiſt,</hi> the <hi>Chymical Emperick,</hi> the <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt,</hi> the <hi>True Chymical Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Shop Chymiſt,</hi> he is Operator and Venditor; a maker and ſeller of <hi>Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Medicines in his Shop: The <hi>Chymical Emperick</hi> he is Operator and Practitioner; a maker and practiſer with <hi>Chymical</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines: The <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt,</hi> he is Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culator and Practiſer; an approver or lover of <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer with them, but not operator; he does not make not exerciſe himſelf in <hi>Chymical</hi> operations.</p>
               <p>The <hi>True Chymical Phyſitian,</hi> he is Speculator, Operator and Practiſer. It
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59336:30"/>is his ſtudy, exerciſe and practice.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Shop Chymiſt</hi> makes and ſells Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Medicines, as the <hi>Apothecary</hi> does the <hi>Galenick</hi> Medicines; they learn their Art by Apprentiſhips and manual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, not by Philoſophical inſtruction and learned education. Their Trade is making and ſelling of Medicines, and to be directed by the Phyſitian in the legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate artificial preparation thereof, who alone is, at leaſt ought to be <hi>Magiſter Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> theſe are miniſterial and ſubordinate to him, and are to be confined within that ſtation; their buſineſs extends no farther in Medicines then their Shop, where their Trade is: the practice of Phyſick belongs not to theſe; and this <hi>Chymiſt</hi> is not a <hi>Chymical Phyſitian,</hi> nor is he quallified for any ſuch employment; if otherwiſe he does, then he falls under the Cenſure of a <hi>Chymical Emperick,</hi> and is to be taken for no other: but if he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows his Trade honeſtly, making Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines faithfully, and with skill accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rules of Art, his Calling is juſt and uſeful; and may ſupply the wants of Chymical Phyſitians, in ſuch Medicines as their own accommodations cannot furniſh them with.</p>
               <p>But if this man be not both able and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59336:31"/>honeſt, his Trade is moſt dangerous, and the greateſt Cheat of all others; and therefore this Trade ought moſt ſtrictly to be looked into and examined: for from this <hi>Chymiſt</hi> the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the moſt of their <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines, and they are diſperſed into all parts of the Kingdom, from <hi>London</hi> into the Countrey <hi>Apothecaries</hi> hands, for the uſe of Phyſitians: the Phyſitian though he be a <hi>Galenick</hi> practiſer, yet oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times preſcribes theſe <hi>Chymical</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and takes them upon truſt, as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary</hi> does, ſuppoſing them to be good and faithfully made.</p>
               <p>Now if theſe Medicines be ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and fallacious, or unskilfully, or negligently prepared, (as too many are) I need not tell you what injury they do.</p>
               <p>This is a general Concern and worth taking notice; every ſick man may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to take his ſhare here, good or bad.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="tract">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59336:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> V. <hi>The Chymical Emperick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis man is very injurious to the Learned <hi>Chymical</hi> Phyſitian, whom he fallaciouſly does perſonate and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: by whoſe ignorance and dangerous practice, a ſcandal is brought upon <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines, and the true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of that Art, the people not well diſcerning the one from the other, think them all alike, and the miſcarriages of theſe fellows defame the very name of <hi>Chymiſt:</hi> but I ſhall inform you, and let you underſtand the great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Emperick, and the Chymical Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Emperical Chymiſt</hi> for the moſt part is ſome broken Tradeſman, or other perſon of decayed fortunes, that takes ſhelter here to ſupport himſelf, by deluding incautelous people not knowing how to detect this deceitful Chymiſt, <hi>Nullus tam ſtupidus Phormio eſt,
<note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>citag.</note> vel Davus qui fruſtra omnibus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam tuendi rationibus tentatis, demum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on profiteatur Medicinam,</hi> ſayes <hi>Freita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius.</hi> There is none ſo dull a block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59336:32"/>having tryed in vain other ſhifts to live, but at laſt he can practice Phyſick. This is the Aſylum and refuge that many men betake them to in their deſperate fortunes. He does not only deceive the Sick, but he defames a learned Art, and the worthy profeſſors of it: elſe, <hi>Si po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus vult decipi, decipiatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if this pretended <hi>Chymiſt</hi> be not ſuch a man as I have deſcribed, forced by fortune to profeſs Phyſick and the Chymical Art; but comes in upon a voluntary ſcore, and is free to live this way, or another way if he pleaſe. Yet if he be not prepared with learning, hath not laid a Philoſophical foundation to fit him for this grand Buſineſs, hath not gone through the whole body of Phyſick, and is well verſt in every part, to qualifie and fit him for practice; this man is but an Emperick, a bold Intruder, a Cheat in this Profeſſion, and a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous man to adviſe or give Phyſick. Hear what <hi>Hypocrates</hi> ſayes for the qualifying and fitting a Phyſitian, whoſoever will get the true knowledge of Phyſick, muſt obtain it by theſe means;
<note place="margin">Hypocrat.</note> 
                  <hi>A natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny and Promptneſs, Learning, Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for Study, Education from his Youth, Induſtry and Time:</hi> But theſe men have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59336:32"/>ſcarce one of theſe qualifications, and yet they dare undertake the Practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and the making of Medicines, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which they rightly underſtand, or are qualified to learn, having no foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to ſtand upon, or praevious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite diſpoſition to initiate them. <hi>Hi Medicinam neſcientes, Medicina abutuntur; &amp; artem egregiam quam non noverunt,
<note place="margin">Rodericus Epiſt. in Speculo ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vitae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitentur; Medicinae excellenti &amp; illuſtri no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine gloriantur, &amp; quaeſtus gratia pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam, ut finem, quaerunt.</hi> They are the words of <hi>Rodericus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Zamora,</hi> complaining of the Empericks of thoſe times: and ſo goes on; <hi>Adde quod multa millia hominum talium Medicorum inſipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia aut inexperientia cadant, quod dum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num morbum curare ſatagunt, plures indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt.</hi> Although the Chymical Emperick and the <hi>Galenick,</hi> are much alike in their qualifications to practice Phyſick, that what is ſaid of the one may ſerve to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipher and warn you of the other, that I need not name them diſtinctly; yet more particularly I ſhall deſcribe the <hi>Cheating Chymiſt,</hi> who is the more dangerous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the two, and a diſgrace to the moſt learned profound art of <hi>Chymiſtry.</hi> At his very firſt deſigning and entrance upon Phyſick, he falls to work upon the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59336:33"/>making of Medicines, and practiſing upon the Sick: he never thinks that ſeven years ſtudy is required, and little enough to lay a foundation before practice; no, he cannot ſtay ſo long; he is for preſent get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Money, not for ſpending of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. And now he begins to practice, he is an expert learned Phyſitian, the very firſt day he begins: he boaſts of great Cures he hath done, and what is it he cannot cure? He will talk as confidently, and lye as handſomly, as if he had been at the Trade a long time; telling you what wonderful Cures he hath performed, and what Patients have gone through his hands. <hi>Nihil audacia doctius, &amp; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia audacius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hypocrat.</note> He brags much of his Experience, for Reaſon he can produce little. He takes the Title of Chymical Doctor upon him, when perhaps he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw the inſide of a Univerſity; he vilifies Univerſity Learning, but loves Univerſity Honour, and thinks himſelf wronged if you call him not Doctor: if you ſpeak of a Doctor of Phyſick that is ſo indeed; he ſlights his Title, and counts Degrees of no value; but the Doctoral Title he hath conferred on himſelf, that he expects you take good notice of, and reverence him for. He gains his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59336:33"/>a new way, not by Univerſity Philoſophy, nor in the Schools; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Furnaces; and he is <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus per ignem,</hi> a Philoſopher by the Fire; and they that meddle with them are ſure to burn their fingers.</p>
               <p>This <hi>working Chymiſt</hi> we will conſider him as <hi>Inceptor,</hi> in the beginning of his practice; or as <hi>Adeptus,</hi> by the length of time more experienced in making Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. At firſt, he is a barbarous fellow and kills deſperately; and few ſcape (that comes in his Clutches) without a miſchief, but carrie about them memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to's of his Craft. He falls to work at firſt daſh with <hi>Antimony</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> and makes Medicines enough to depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late a City. After many ſad diſaſters in his practice, he begins to be more wary; and by doleful experience (to the Sick) is taught to make more ſafe and gentle Medicines: <hi>Jam melius didicit pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculis veſtris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By time, if the man be ingenious and follows his work diligently, in meliora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Medicines and improving his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments; is well accommodated with a Laboratory and Utenſils; he will be able to make ſome good Medicines, and becomes a better operator then formerly;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59336:34"/>but a great many have paid dearly for his skill; but their mouths are ſtopt with earth that they cannot complain of his hard uſage, and he proceeds on in his practice boldly and ſmoothly: and now (after his long Adventures and hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Experiments to inſtruct him) we will be ſo candid and favourable to him in our opinions, as to conſider him equal with the Shop Chymiſt, and ſuppoſe him to underſtand the working part of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> that he is able to make any Medicine according to the progreſs laid down in any Author or Pharmacopeian.</p>
               <p>And now being arrived hither, if he would leave practiſing upon the Sick, and keep only to making of Medicines, and make them faithfully to ſell, for the uſe of Phyſitians, <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> or others that deſire them; or be an operator to Phyſitians, and <hi>Tyroe's in Chymiſtry;</hi> this man might live more happily and free from blame. But he is loth to leave his old wont; <hi>Bonus odor lucri</hi>—though unjuſtly gotten: his practiſe brought in Money; and having uſurped the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorſhip, he thinks ſcorn to be degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and take his own proper Title a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; he will be a Doctor ſtill, ſo long as any body will think him ſo, or repair
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59336:34"/>to him; and rather then his Cuſtom ſhall fail, he will have twenty crafty tricks to hook in Patients. Such Medicaſters as theſe, <hi>London</hi> now abounds with, &amp; other parts of the Kingdom has too many ſuch ſcattered here and there, to the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of Phyſick,
<note place="margin">Freitag.</note> and the learned Profeſſors. <hi>Impoſturas horum medicaſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum emendet Magiſtratus &amp; Caveat vulgus,</hi> it belongs to the Magiſtrate to reform theſe abuſes, and the people to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of ſuch Impoſtors.</p>
               <p>Here I ſhall leave this <hi>Cheating Chymiſt</hi> at his cunning deceits and jugling with his Patients, and ſhew you his Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and Ability to practice Phyſick, ſuppoſing him at the beſt (which few of them attain to) a good operator and prepater of <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs, to make good Medicines, and be well skilled in <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> is one good part of a Phyſitian, nay a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part; but where is all the reſt to compleat him? Here is a Body but no Head; here are Medicines but where is Skill to uſe them: there is a great deal more required to qualifie a Phyſitian, beſides Medicines. I can take a Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and learn him to make Medicine in ſome reaſonable time, but what then?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59336:35"/>I may make him a good work-man, but not a good Phyſitian: this man I may teach to work well with his hands, but he is not capable to work with his head: he has not the rudiments and ground-work of Philoſophy to fit and capacitate him for ſuch an employment.</p>
               <p>That man which intends the practice of Phyſick, muſt be qualified with good Literature, and lay a Philoſophical foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that he may be able to diſcourſe and reaſon with himſelf, the cauſes and effects of things, both in Nature and Art: that he may be able to judge and examine the Opinions and Doctrine of men in the ſame faculty, to adhere to this or that according to right reaſon. The Furniture required to accommodate and fit a Phyſitian is much, and requires a good time to be gathering together: he muſt be inſtituting and fitting up from his youth, taking in Literature betimes, <hi>(Ars longa, vita brevis est)</hi> and gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally compleating ſtep by ſtep, from one part of Learning to another, untill he be throughly qualified for the Art or Science he is deſigned for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ubi deſinit Phyſicus, ibi incipit Medicus.</hi> A man is not to meddle with Phyſick untill he has run through Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59336:35"/>this is the foundation he ſtands upon: and when he comes to the ſtudy of Phyſick, <hi>Ars Medendi,</hi> he has a long progreſs to make before he comes to the <hi>Pharmaceutick</hi> part, the contrivance of Medicines; this is the laſt work he hath to do, he is now come to the top of the Ladder, here he finiſheth his Courſe, and having gained this he is compleat. But this <hi>Emperick</hi> skips all the reſt, and mounts to the top at firſt: if this man do not catch a fall, he is ſure to make many one lye low for it: he begins where the true Phyſitian ends; he falls to work upon Medicines, before he underſtands the nature of Humane Bodies or Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Materials he works upon, or the Rules of his Art he pretends to.</p>
               <p>But this man you will ſay has learned by long Experience to make good Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, now he may practice ſafely? No, admit he has; good Tools do not make a good Artiſt: he that makes Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgical Inſtruments is as unskilful in Chirurgery as another man. If you bring me the Tools and Inſtruments of the beſt Watch-maker; yet I cannot make a Watch; I cannot uſe them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have not the whole deſign of the work in my head: ſo this working Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59336:36"/>ſuppoſe he has good Medicines, yet what can he do with them, if he do not underſtand the whole Art of Phyſick, he cannot practice knowingly and ſafely as an honeſt man ought to do: you may as well kill a man with a Cordial, as with another Medicine; you may kill a man with a good Medicine as well as with a bad, if the condition of the Patient be not conſidered according to the indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: if you give a, good Medicine out of ſeaſon, and neglect opportunity, if you give one Medicine when the caſe requires another; a Purge when a Cordial is required; or a Cordial, when a Purge or other Medicine is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; the opportunity perhaps is gone of doing this man good. There is a time and ſeaſon to be obſerved, when Medicine is to be given this or that as the occaſion does call for, which none but the skilful Phyſitian underſtands; who knows the nature of the Diſeaſe, its progreſs, complications, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Patients body.</p>
               <p>The making of Medicines is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to qualifie you for a Phyſitian; there is a great deal more belongs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh a Phyſitian beſides that: a man may be a good work-man in hewing and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59336:36"/>carving a piece of Timber, yet may be very unfit to contrive the Building of a Ship; he muſt have the whole Deſign and Frame of ſuch a work in his head, conſidering every material appertaining that it be exact and proportionate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Rule, that the whole may be compleat in the ſeveral parts of it. You ſuppoſe this Chymiſt can make a good Medicine: what then? This does not make him a good Phyſitian; he is only an operator, a good work-man at beſt: but uſing and deſigning Medicines right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is a profound Art, requires great knowledge which is not obtained but by long time, and a diligent Series of ſtudy. This Chymiſt begins at the wrong end, he begins with making of Medicines, and neglects all the reſt that belongs to this Learned Art; but the true Phyſitian he finiſheth his ſtudy and ends with Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; then enters upon practice.</p>
               <p>The inſufficiency of theſe men in Learning; their inability to acquire a ſound, requiſite, Philoſophical know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by this prepoſterous indirect courſe, is apparent to reaſonable men, that ſuch are deceivers of the Sick and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſers of a moſt learned and noble Art. And therefore it behoves all that have
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59336:37"/>a regard to their ſafety, to beware leaſt they fall into the hands of ſuch impoſtors, that fallaciouſly perſonate the Learned Chymical Phyſitian, and impudently uſurp the Doctoral Title; that vilifie and reproach men of Learning, deſpiſe their Degrees, and ſcoff at Univerſities as a ridiculous Education, which nothing but the bold front of Ignorance, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Knavery and Envy could do the like. And now I leave them to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by thoſe, which have a power, and ought to reform theſe grand abuſes, and give due incouragement to Learning and learned men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="tract">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59336:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> VI. <hi>The practiſing Apothecary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMongſt the Encroachers upon the Faculty of Phyſick, we find the <hi>practiſing Apothecary</hi> uſurping the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians Function, to which formerly he was miniſterial; but has now broke that relation and become magiſterial, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor and practiſer of Phyſick: how this comes about, that the Doctor ſhould be undermined by his Servant, whom he hath intruſted with his Secrets, and put great confidence in, is worth inquiring into: Sure here was great folly in the one to lay open the <hi>Accana's</hi> of his Art, &amp; give occaſion to be ſupplanted and begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; or great knavery in the other to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray his truſt, and uſurp the authority of his Maſter. Whether of the two is more to be blamed and cenſured, though in a different reſpect, is hard to ſay, for both are highly guilty. But we will proceed to a farther examination of this Matter.</p>
               <p>How long have you been a practiſer of Phyſick? <hi>Apoth.</hi> Almoſt ever ſince Phyſitians deſerted the making of their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59336:38"/>Medicines: though they be ſo careleſs to neglect the weightieſt part of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and reſign the moſt difficult part of their Art into the hands of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to manage; yet I am an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man and had rather do more then I ought, then leſs: and therefore I think I am not to be blamed ſo much as they.</p>
               <p>Who taught you this trick of practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Phyſick? That does not belong to your Trade, you are only to make and ſell, you are not to adviſe, and take charge of the Sick, you forget the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Ne Sutor ultra crepidam. Apoth.</hi> I learned it of my Maſter, he got many a fair pound by it; he gained the love of his Neighbours and Friends by ſaving them the expence of Fees; and got Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom to his Shop by it.</p>
               <p>But how dare you to practice Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick? That's a great Undertaking, a grand Buſineſs which requires much knowledge and great skill to manage, you only know how to make the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. <hi>Apoth.</hi> 'Tis true, I do not ſolidly underſtand the whole body of Phyſick, but I underſtand a Medicine better then he that preſcribes it; ſo if I be defective in the other parts of Phyſick, he is in Medicines, for I correct his Bill ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59336:38"/>elſe it would not be <hi>ſecundum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem;</hi> therefore I think my ſelf not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to practice, nor of the worſt ſort of Empericks that underſtand neither Diſeaſes nor Medicines.</p>
               <p>But Friend, the Phyſitians deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the pharmacopoietical part, does not countenance you to be pragmatick, nor qualifie you in the other parts of Phyſick; and you have reaſon to thank him for being ſo, elſe where had been your Trade? He parted with the Secrets of his Art to ſet you up: now had not you better follow your Trade honeſtly, and not uſurp the Phyſitians Function; whereby you will ſhew your gratitude, and acknowledgements for this great kindneſs, and own what you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him. <hi>Apoth.</hi> Truly, the number of our Trade does much increaſe, and we are ſo many of us, and the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Empericks ſo abound, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get enough by ſelling in my Shop, except I go abroad and practice: beſides, the Medicines of my Shop are ſo many, I muſt find a way to vend them, or they will be ſpoiled before they be ſpent.</p>
               <p>Although this does not excuſe you in the Injury done to Phyſitians, yet if it be ſo as you ſay, it mitigates your fault
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59336:39"/>
                  <hi>à tanto;</hi> but why do you not ſeek a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, by better and more careful means; by conſulting the Phyſitians, whoſe Candor towards you is ſuch, they will be ready to joyn and aſſiſt your Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in rectifying and obviating thoſe inconveniencies for the future, you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of; by preventing the ſwelling number and great increaſe of Traders. By contracting and taking off the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and ſupernumeraries of your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licines impoſed upon you; and by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Chymical Empericks and all other illegal practiſers: which being done (as it is not very difficult to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected) the Buſineſs of Phyſick will lie between the Phyſitians and your ſelves; and then you will have no Cauſe or Plea to exceed the bounds of your Trade, nor the Phyſitians juſt Cauſe to complain of you, as they have at this day.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Apothecary,</hi> if you practice and be much abroad, viſiting your Patients, who muſt manage your Buſineſs at home? <hi>Apoth.</hi> My Boyes can do the Buſineſs in the Shop, they can make Medicines and ſerve Cuſtomers, and if a Phyſitians Bill come they can make up the Medicine well enough to ſerve turn.</p>
               <p>But what if the Boyes ſhould miſtake,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59336:39"/>or for want of Care and Skill, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine be ill made, will not that reflect upon you, if it do not operate well, according to the intention of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. <hi>Apoth.</hi> No, I can come off well enough, I can ſay the Medicine was made according to the Preſcription; the Doctor cannot diſprove me, let the fault lie at his door: I muſt look after my oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions abroad; my Servants are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to do the Buſineſs at home; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be alwayes in my Shop, nor will I tye my ſelf to wait upon his Buſineſs, but at my own conveniency: 'tis true, we were at firſt but <hi>Miniſtri Medicorum;</hi> but now we are in a fair way to be <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicorum Magiſtri:</hi> we can bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practice, and we can put them out of practice when we pleaſe: if we do but whiſper in the Patients ear, this Doctor does not preſcribe well; he comes no more there, another is ſent for that we like bettter, that uſeth our Shop, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our humour: our words goe far in the opinion of the Patient, and except he be very much preingaged and bent upon a Phyſitian, we can ſway him this way or that way as our intereſt leads us; but if he names a Chymical Phyſitian, one that makes his own Medicines, we
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59336:40"/>cry him down might and main, he ſpoils our Trade; we can ſay he is a Quack, or a man of no parts (though he be the ableſt Phyſitian in the Town) that his Medicines are mineral Phyſick and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; we will blaſt his Credit if it be poſſible; he ſhall have no Reputation if our words can defame him: but he that practiſeth at our own Shop, that ſends his Bills hither; that is the beſt Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, and him only we adviſe you to.</p>
               <p>'Tis enough; we underſtand now the myſtery and deſign of your Trade; your unlawful practice of Phyſick, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Sick; your encroachments upon Phyſitians, and ſecret injuries. We underſtand now the <hi>Apothecary's</hi> advice and kindneſs to the Patient in the choice of a Phyſitian; his judgement and cenſure of Phyſitians, upon what Bias it runs.</p>
               <p>When Phyſick was in its Infancy, and after it began to increaſe and have good growth in <hi>Hypocrates</hi> &amp; <hi>Galen</hi>'s times, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians then managed the whole Buſineſs themſelves, there was no <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> but the careful induſtrious Phyſitian prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his own Medicines and would not intruſt ſo great a Concern in the hand of others: but when Phyſick came into a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59336:40"/>general repute and uſe; Phyſitians few, and Patients many; they began to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the preparation of their medicines to others, whom they did inſtruct and train up in Pharmacy, and were wholly gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and commanded by the Phyſitian, and were very obſequious &amp; uſefull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to him: but theſe having gained the knowledge of Medicines, a freedome in making and ſelling, and by time pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of incorporation; the caſe is altered now, the Phyſician hath loſt his faithfull ſervant, he is now independent, an Apothecary; yes, and a Phyſitian too, and thinks himſelf as well intereſſed and concerned in Phyſick as the Doctor and interferes with him in his practice. <hi>Freitagius</hi> checks the boldneſs of theſe men very ſharply;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Abuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> medicina pag.</hi> 97.</note> 
                  <hi>Nimis audax impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densque facin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt Pharmacopoeos ſcientiae quadam frivola opinione infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>os velle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta morbis remedia inconſulto medico, auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toramento proprio, ventoſa arrogantia &amp; confidentia plus quam Cyclopica decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſtrange that our predeceſſors had not the Prognoſtick of this in their heads, to obviate the miſchiefe that might befall their ſucceſſors; that they did not conſult what might happen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59336:41"/>on the Introduction of Sub-ordinate men, and committing the <hi>Arcana's</hi> of art to their truſt; that they did not as well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt the infidelity and encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe, as deſign their own eaſe and preſent conveniency. Tis plain they did not, and the ill conſequents are as evident: give an inch and they take an ell; Phyſicians gave them the profit of Medicines, but they take the benefit of practiſing too, and ask no leave: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of Medicines they challenge as properly belonging to them; the next will be a propriety in practice (they are not ſatisfied with their trade) they would be equall with Phyſitians; and having gained that,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>es ut fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les; aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the next endeavour is to be above them: Succeſs begets boldneſs, and incourageth farther attempts; win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners know not how to leave off their game. Many of theſe Apothecaries are grown very confident in the Practice of Phyſick, and cuſtome which makes all things familiar, will legitimate and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them in the opinion of common people; ſuch thriving leaders ſhall not want followers, tis caſie to gueſs then what will be the iſſue and event of it this is a bad omen and ſeems to threaten the Crown; which undoubtedly will
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59336:41"/>fall upon this faculty (as it comes on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace) if not timely prevented by the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and unanimous conſent of the Profeſſors. The only means to avert this ill fate: and although the <hi>Seniors</hi> that are well planted may think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure and that the ſtorm will not happen in their days; yet they cannot but be ſenſible of the great encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and injuries now offered to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; which will fall much heavier upon the <hi>Juniors,</hi> not ſo able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend but muſt truckle.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Thomſon</hi> noting the abuſes in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick does not without cauſe charge many of them upon the imprudence of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, in the il management of their own buſineſs.
<q>Tis true, ſaith he, there are ſad exorbitancies,
<note place="margin">Galius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> irregularities and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Phyſick, but who we pray have been the principal occaſions of them but your ſelves? who have conjured up ſuch ſwarms of Quacks in every place (who like Locuſts eate the bread out of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Phyſitians mouths) by your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane preſcripts. — If they had better practiſed the Pythagotical doctrine, theſe things had never been; or had ye delivered your ſelves, as ye find fault</q> 
                  <hi>Paraecelſus, Helmont,</hi> and other ſons of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59336:42"/>art did, more aenigmatically, who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw theſe miſchiefs, and endeavoured to prevent them, Phyſick had flouriſhed to this day in its ſplendor and beauty.</p>
               <p>Dr.
<note place="margin">Vindiciae medicinae &amp; medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
                  <hi>Hodges</hi> treats upon this Subject, <hi>of practiſing Apothecaries;</hi> wherein he ſets forth the great abuſe offered to this learned faculty by ſuch men, and ſhews their inſufficiency for that undertaking. I ſhall recite ſome part.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Indeed ſuch is the increaſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries company,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 62.</note> that all of them cannot reaſonably expect imployment, who therefore hunt abroad after Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and prey one upon anothers buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; theſe inconveniencies would be remedied if the counſell of a grave w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was obſerved, who adviſeth the magiſtrate to be very carefull not to to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate more Apothecaries then are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the diſcharge of that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; implying that if they ſuper-aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they would moſt infallibly injure the publick, and rather then their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for want of timely uſe ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay and grow worthleſs, chooſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſpend them by their own practice, and think it a leſs crime to harm the people then ſuffer any damage in their Shop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and when theſe <hi>practiſing Apothecarie</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59336:42"/>have by their inſinuations inveigled ſome to take Phyſick of them, as it is not improbable but that theſe being ignorant of the direct way of curing diſeaſes, muſt neceſſarily hereupon ſpend more medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines then Phyſitians who exactly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is to be done, will not multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply preſcripts to tire out their patients and advance their charge; ſo how can ſuch Patients aſſure themſelves that their Apothecary Phyſitians doe not make uſe of that opportunity as much to rid their ſhop of Phyſick, as them of diſeaſes; however if the whole is caſt up, ſuch Patients will find no cauſe to commend the cheapneſs of their cure in reſpect of what it had been, if they had conſulted Phyſitians; not to mention that ſome of theſe do confidently take and demand fees for their viſits, beſides the profitable income by their Phyſick. I may ſafely affirm that moſt of them can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford to be ſo charitable as to wait on their Patients without ſome recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for their time and trouble, which are uſually accounted in the price of the medicine: So then what a deluſion doe they lye under who ſeek to theſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, hoping thereby to ſave Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians fees.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59336:43"/>
               <p>
                  <q>This Author in the ſame Chapter ſets forth the office and buſineſs of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 55.</note> circumſcribing him within the bounds of his trade; and farther ſhews his inſufficiency and inability for the practice of phyſick, notwithſtanding the preſcripts of Phyſitians upon the file in their keeping.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 56, 67.</note> He likewiſe ſhews their infidelity and breach of truſt with Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians by this their unlawful practiſing;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 60, 61.</note> and the danger that does attend their attempts upon the ſick; neglecting their proper buſines at home in their ſhops and leaving that to the management of raw Apprentices; which is very injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous both to Phyſitians and Patients. Then he inſerts two edicts publiſhed by the Magiſtrates of <hi>Bruſſels,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 67.</note> upon good conſideration, to check the boldneſs of theſe men; and to be a pattern to other States and Princes equally concerned herein; and to manifeſt that it is not ſo much the Phyſitians as the peoples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt that the Apothecary be not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to practice.</q> But if there be not a coercive power to reſtrain them here; and theſe men perſiſt obſtinate in their unlawful practice; endeavouring to bring the Practice of Phyſick, within the limits of their trade, as much profeſſing to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59336:43"/>Phyſick as to prepare or ſell it; then the Counſell or remedy propoſed by this Author, is the beſt expedient for Phyſitians to defend themſelves, and this their ſacred art from being proſtitute to the rude invaſion of illegal pretenders; by aſſuming the whole buſineſs of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick themſelves, as our Anceſtors did, who prepared their own medicines, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining their ſecrets within their owne cloſets.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If theſe becauſe of their ſettlement as free traders ſhall hereupon deſtroy the relation between Phyſitians and them,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 54.</note> as if their intereſt did not much conſiſt in the practice of Phyſitians, they will have no cauſe of complaint, if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Phyſick take their buſineſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in their own hands, and imitate the moſt ſucceſsful practice of their renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned predeceſſors.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="tract">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:59336:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> VII. <hi>The Rigid Galeniſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galenick</hi> Phyſitians are of two ſorts: the Rigid <hi>Galeniſt,</hi> and the <hi>Galeno-Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</hi> The Rigid <hi>Galeniſt</hi> is ſo ſtrait la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and tyed up to the principles and doctrine of his Maſter <hi>Galen,</hi> that all his buſineſs is to underſtand the ſenſe and meaning of this grand Patron: ſo that if he have but <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> of his ſide, he ſeeks no further; That is truth, &amp; That he thinks is weapon and armour ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to oppoſe all Antagoniſts.</p>
               <p>This Profeſſor he is ſo feeble and weak in his parts, he cannot goe alone without leading: he cannot write nor preſcribe, but his Maſter muſt hold his pen: he dares not truſt his own reaſon and experience, but is always a practiſer by the book; a Scholler always, never maſter of his art. He drudges for the credit of his Maſter, never goes out of the circle of his doctrine, he thinks all Phyſical truths to be repoſited and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in the works of <hi>Galen.</hi> The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perfection he aimes at is to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe; accounting them the <hi>ne plus
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59336:44"/>ultrà,</hi> the bounds and limits of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in the medicinal ſcience; and to goe beyond or beſide them, is to ſtray from the Canonical truth.</p>
               <p>He aſſents to all he reads, not by a well grounded approbation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of his own reaſon; but freely yields to the authority of his maſter, and thinks it good manners not to contradict him. He troubles not himſelf with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, being prepoſſeſſed and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Theorems and Theſes of his maſter are undoubted truths.</p>
               <p>If you quote <hi>van Helmont</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Philoſopher he laughs, as if you had named a mad man; and wanting depth of Reaſon to fathom his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; he vilifies, becauſe he does not underſtand; and it makes as little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon him as Epiſcopal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity does upon a Quaker.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chymical</hi> Phyſitians he ſuperci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſly looks upon as ſo many <hi>Vulcans:</hi> he ſcorns to ſully himſelf with Furnaces, Coals and Glaſſes; or to keep an Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator in his houſe for that purpoſe; he is no ſuch Mechanick Profeſſor. Thoſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> in Phyſick he cannot endure; becauſe they contradict <hi>Galen;</hi> which he accounts an abſurd audacity, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59336:45"/>blaſphemy againſt the Truth.</p>
               <p>He makes Medicines with his Pen; (a very fine Invention) his Head and his Hands being unexperienced in Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Experiments and Tryals: but the faults and errors he commits in this new way of <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> he leaves to his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector to be amended according to his diſcretion, and gives him authority, <hi>Fiat ſecundum artem.</hi> Chymical Medicines he will have nothing to do with; he cryes, they are dangerous; (but he knows not what they are) and this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a Confidence in ſome ſilly Patients that he is a judicious and a wary man.</p>
               <p>He is known by many good women in the Town, to be an able man and a ſafe practiſer; if he does no good, he will do no harm; they know his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines to be very harmleſs, ſuch as they uſe to make themſelves, <hi>Syrups, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, Decoctions, Ptiſans, Juleps, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He labours not to improve or bring any additional diſcoveries to the Art he Profeſſeth, but plods on in the common road of Tradition: he will tell you, he tryes no Experiments, he practiſeth as they did 500 years ago; that if you be killed you die by Art, he can ſhew you a Rule for it, and an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:59336:45"/>
               <p>He thinks it not poſſible to out-do what is done already, and counts it an affected ſingularity and ridiculous pride to attempt any thing beyond the induſtry of our famous Predeceſſors. He dotes upon <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and reliſheth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a <hi>junior ſtanding:</hi> in Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he asks you what Authority you can alledge for your determination? Not what Reaſon; what Example in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice you follow, and who is your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor? Not what Experience and what Reaſon to confirm and eſtabliſh your Judgement. If he loſe his Book, you muſt loſe your Phyſitian; for he practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not by his own Reaſon and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, but by the Reaſon and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of others; and hunts among his Books for an Example, which is his Rule, and without that he dates not proceed.</p>
               <p>The Medical Art he accounts long ſince compleated, that there is no room left for Invention, and therefore he ſits down and cuns his Leſſon, he is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be no wiſer then his Maſters: but the <hi>Chymical</hi> Phyſitians thoſe <hi>innovators</hi> in Phyſick he cannot endure, becauſe they will not be ſatisfied, but are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes labouring for variety in Phyſick,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59336:46"/>and making new diſcoveries; examining and calling in queſtion Opinions of 1000 years ſtanding; exploding the Principles and Poſitions of the Antients; throwing down &amp; ſetting up; he cannot approve of ſuch diſturbances and wrangling contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies: for his part he loves quietneſs, declines vain diſputings, hates new no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and would not be diſturbed in the plain way of practice he hath learned; nor ſtartled and juſtled out of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by a ſtrange unheard of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and begin to learn <hi>de novo.</hi> But is willing to live and die with the old Doctrine he is acquainted with, right or wrong.</p>
               <p>If you would know more of this mans abilities and excellent parts, ask his <hi>Apothecary;</hi> he will tell you he is the ableſt Phyſitian in Town, if you inquire as a Patient: but if upon another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, you be intimate and freely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, he will tell you another tale.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="tract">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:59336:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> VIII. <hi>The Galeno-Chymist.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LIbavius</hi> diſtinguiſheth <hi>Galeniſts</hi> thus: <hi>Galenici ſunt duplices: quidam ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ded. Becariſio.</note> qui nihil ne latum quidem unguem à Dogmatibus Galeni ſibi diſcedendum putant. Quidam nullius addicti jurare in verba ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtri, liberalem amplectuntur diſciplinam, &amp; ingenuê in Medicina verſantur, auſi vel ipſum Galenum reprehendere &amp; Hypocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſicubi à vero diſcedunt. Manent tamen intra veterum Praeceptorum Scholae Galenicae ſepta, candemque medendi tenent conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem.</hi> The diſtinction is good, and therefore I ſhall render it to every Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity: <hi>Galeniſts</hi> (ſayes he) are of two ſorts; ſome are ſervile, who think they muſt not diſſent a jot from the opinions of <hi>Galen;</hi> (this is <hi>the rigid Galeniſt:</hi>) others not bound to aſſert the Tenents of any grand Teacher, do embrace Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the Art of Phyſick freely and ingeniouſly, that dare to reprehend <hi>Galen</hi> himſelf and <hi>Hypocrates</hi> if they ſwerve from the Truth. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they retain the old Precepts of the <hi>Galenick School,</hi> and follow the ſame
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59336:47"/>method of Curing. This ſutes with the <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt,</hi> and he goes a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for he is Chymically inclined.</p>
               <p>To give you a deſcription and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of the <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt;</hi> he is a legitimate Phyſitian, Philoſophical and accompliſh'd with Literature; and we will ſuppoſe him doctorated; an ingenious <hi>Galeniſt</hi> according to this deſcription of <hi>Libavius;</hi> a practiſer with <hi>Galenick</hi> and <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines: he loves, at leaſt he allows <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> to be a good and ſafe way of preparing Medicines; he views over the Precepts and Doctrine of this Art ſometimes; he is a Speculator only, no Operator; he is not exerciſed in the manual operation and proceſs of theſe Medicines, nor Inſpector over his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants or others, to be practically expert in Chymical tryals and preparations.</p>
               <p>I cannot ſay he is a <hi>True Chymical Phyſitian,</hi> he is only well qualified for a <hi>Tyro:</hi> he cannot direct, correct, judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly approve or appoint a Chymical Medicine, upon his own knowledge, but depends upon the judgement of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Authors, and is biaſſed uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Opinions and Approbations of this or that Writer, as he fancies his abilities. This Learned Phyſitian I pity,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59336:47"/>becauſe he is not <hi>ſuis numeris abſolutus;</hi> he halts upon one Leg; he muſt lean and reſt himſelf upon the uncertain and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious tradition of Authors; who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes collect from one another, take up upon truſt, and aſſert the vertues of many Medicines, of which they never tryed the proceſs or the uſe. I have ſome reaſon to ſay this; having been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon this ſcore, and my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions fruſtrated in Medicines, after much trouble and pains in the proceſs thereof, depending upon the verity of Tradition for my Guide: therefore ſay I, <hi>(Experto Crede)</hi> a Speculator in Chymiſtry, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon that judgement to appoint Chymical Medicines, deceives himſelf and wrongs the Sick; for the knowledge thereof is not gained but by manual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and pharmacopoietical experience; elſe his judgement is preſumed, and his Preſcript hazardous: he muſt be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in making, or he ſhall never be able to give a good account of them; nor can he judiciouſly chuſe or reject this or that, to know which is a laudable good Medicine, and which is noxious or fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous, but by obſervation in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and tryals of making, as well as in the uſe.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:59336:48"/>
               <p>For theſe Reaſons which might be amplified much more at large, I wiſh the Learned <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt</hi> who is <hi>Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymicus</hi> and but Speculator was <hi>Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus practicus,</hi> an Operator in <hi>Chymical Pharmacy;</hi> he would then more cloſely embrace the Principles and Doctrine of this profound Art, and be eager in the exerciſe thereof; he would not then tye up Chymical Medicines ſo ſtrictly to <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenick</hi> Rules; this Harneſs does not well fit them, it is too ſtrait; they act more freely, generouſly and univerſally: not a methodically and at random to be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited; but rightly uſed, are limited and preſcribed by the greateſt reaſon; though not conformable in all points, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the <hi>Galenick</hi> method.</p>
               <p>This Learned <hi>Galeno-Chymist</hi> is ſo knowing by his theorical inſpection into Chymiſtry; that he judgeth and eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines to excell all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their power and efficacy; that this way of preparing Medicines is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and ingenious; becoming only, and an Art for the beſt and moſt ſublime Philoſophers, and truly learned men, to be employed therein. Yet this ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Phyſitian is intangled in the <hi>Galenick</hi> Practice, he cannot well get out: he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59336:48"/>knows the <hi>Chymical</hi> Phyſitians are in the beſt way to improve the Medical Science; to redeem the Profeſſion out of rude profane hands; and to regain the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and worthy eſteem of the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: he knows they are the moſt laudable practiſers, and their induſtry and labour in Medicines is moſt legitimate, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of the ancient moſt famous Profeſſors; treaſuring up <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's,</hi> and repoſiting them in the cuſtody of the Sons of Art, communicable only to the <hi>Aeſculapian</hi> Family; hating pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this divine Art: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, the current of his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice runs in another Channel; and he acts not according to the integrity of his judgement and reaſon which informs him another Courſe, but biaſſed with the ſiniſter perſwaſions of the preſent Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Eaſe, Intereſt, the trouble and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of croſſing the ſtream, and ſailing with another wind; he goes on againſt the checks of his own reaſon; and he cannot but ſay, upon a ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; <hi>Video meliora proboque, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riora ſequor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt</hi> ſhall ſay; I am a Chymical Phyſitian as good as the beſt; I practice with Chymical Medicines,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59336:49"/>when I think it convenient, and where the caſe requires ſuch, and when it does not I uſe <hi>Galenick</hi> Medicines; nor is this practice inconſiſtent with a true Artiſt, to this is anſwered; in that you uſe Chymical Medicines, and ſometimes <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenick,</hi> according to the exigency of the occaſion, and rightly diſtinguiſhing the Caſe, what is properly required, this is allowed to be rational and good: I am not ſo ſevere, to throw out all <hi>Galenick</hi> Medicines, and baniſh them the practice of Phyſick, but that ſome of them may be retained; yet with correction, the incongruities of Compoſition and inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencies of Preparation being altered and amended. But how can you juſtifie the uſe and appointment of <hi>Chymical</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines (judiciouſly, knowingly, <hi>per autopſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> and cautiouſly to be uſed) that you neither ſaw, nor know who was the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator that made them; he was a Cheat, a negligent, or an ignorant perſon, a <hi>Pſeudo-Chymiſt</hi> for ought you know (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly it is ſo) and theſe Medicines are not to be given at ſuch a blind adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but warily and knowingly.</p>
               <p>The uncertainty and hazard a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian runs in this way of practice will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear plainly, if you ſtrictly inquire into
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59336:49"/>theſe two things: firſt how many good Medicines are baſely made and abuſed, that are expoſed to ſale: ſecondly, how many Medicines that ſtand now recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for uſe, and daily ſold; which though never ſo exactly made according to Preſcript, are erroneous bad Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. Let a ſtrict ſearch be made into theſe two points, and then you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with me, that ſuch a practice by unknown Medicines, is not legitimate, not rational, but hazardous: not ſhall you be able to diſcover and judge of theſe two points untill you be a <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoeian,</hi> and then you will ſee clearly the inſufficiencies, deceits and hurtful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of common ſale Medicines.</p>
               <p>How oft does the <hi>common Turbith Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerale,</hi> burn and fret in the Patients body from the negligent preparation? but at beſt is not a good Medicine, and the <hi>Mercury</hi> will revive again. The <hi>Common Antimonium Diaphoreticum</hi> frequently cauſeth Vomitings, contrary to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Medicine and expectation of the Phyſitian, through the negligent and unskilful preparation of it; not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a due fixation, and expelling the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure <hi>Sulphur:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt</hi> is timorous and gives commonly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59336:50"/>under 20 grains; whereas I have given of my own preparation 50 grains with good ſucceſs, and a friendly <hi>Diaphore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Operation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cremor</hi> and <hi>Cryſtals of Tartar ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticated with Allum,</hi> quite contrary to the intention of the Medicine. <hi>Sal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> nothing but a diſguiſed <hi>Vitriol</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. The fixed <hi>Salts of Abſinth, Cochlear, Fraxini, Cardui, Artemiſ. &amp;c.</hi> differing only in Title commonly. The <hi>Chymical Oils</hi> moſt of them adulterated. Indeed what Medicine can you name that is not abuſed; either by the meanneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate condition of the Drugs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients; or leaving out ſomething of value and price, or Subtracting its due proportions; or by inartificial prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through want of skill, care, time and pains; or by the ſuperaddition and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of ſome cheap Ingredient to augment the Medicine: and he that can falſifie a Medicine beſt as not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, thinks he hath attained great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and is an excellent Artiſt. What confidence then can you have in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Medicine? What true obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can you make? And what ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory anſwer can you give, if a certain account of the Medicine be demanded
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59336:50"/>as upon your own knowledge you ought to give? All that you can ſay is; you hope well, that it was ſo and ſo: but is not this hope preſumed, more than ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; for if you inquire abroad, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine into Medicine, you will find the Sophiſticate, negligent prepared and bad Medicines, to be three for one in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to the compleat, honeſt and duly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Medicines.</p>
               <p>Theſe things duly conſidered, as very worthy of ſerious conſideration; I am not out of hopes to ſee this learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian the <hi>Galeno-Chymiſt,</hi> an expert <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoeian</hi> and Chymical Operator; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of <hi>Swelfer</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent pattern, and others the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Profeſſors of this Faculty, both ancient and modern: the Conſequence will be of great advantage to the true Profeſſors thereof; as the only means to reſcue and recover the loſt repute of this moſt excellent Art, now proſtituted and laid open to all pretenders, which ought to lie only in the boſom of the Sons of Art.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="tract">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:59336:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> IX. <hi>Medicus Abſolutus.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The Compleat Chymical Phyſitian.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Jatro-chymiſt</hi> and <hi>Hermetick</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, is educated from his Youth in all neceſſary learning to qualifie and fit him for this grand buſineſs; and that he may be introduced into the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Art legitimately according to the Law of <hi>Hypocrates.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Quiſquis enim Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicina Scientiam ſibi vere comparare volet, eum his ducibus voti ſui compotem fieri opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet; natura, doctrina, loco ſtudiis apto, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione à puero, induſtria &amp; tempore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And having thus gradually received Literature and improvement in the Tongues and Liberal Arts; and being well grounded in Philoſophy, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Nature in general, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Macrocoſme;</hi> he then directs his ſtudy more particularly to the body of man, and contemplates the <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme,</hi> that moſt admirable frame of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the diverſity of its parts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, with the variety of harmonious Functions, all ſubſervient to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59336:51"/>of the whole, directed and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by the <hi>Archaeus</hi> or Spirit of Life, and here he is buſie for ſome conſiderable time in <hi>Phyſiologye,</hi> as the firſt ſtep in Phyſick.</p>
               <p>After this he conſiders the requiſite ſupports of this Machine, what is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Nature to preſerve this humane body in due order, and to maintain it in ſtrength and vigour: and now he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in the <hi>diaetetick</hi> part of Phyſick; appoints and regulates man in his Meat and Drink, in ſleeping and watching, in exerciſe and reſt, aſſignes him a fit place to live in, &amp;c. moſt agreeing and ſuting with his body, the longer to preſerve it. And as Nature does not continue long in the ſtate of integrity and health, but declenſions and diſorders will ariſe, and this exquiſite Fabrick tends towards a diſſolution and decay: he then conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the body of man in its preternatural ſtate, the <hi>Dyſcraſy</hi> and <hi>Alaxy</hi> wherewith it is diſcompoſed, or liable thereto; he is therefore acquainting himſelf with the <hi>Pathological</hi> part of Phyſick, taking cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of all the diſeaſes incident to mans body, in their cauſes, with the Symptomes and Phaenomena that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them: and being well verſt and ſharp
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59336:52"/>fighted in the diſcovery of diſeaſes and their complications; he next applyes himſelf and conſults what is fit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to reduce and recover back again this loſt health, and vigorous ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; firſt <hi>qua methodo,</hi> how this muſt be done, and here the <hi>methodus medendi</hi> directs and regulates him: ſecondly, <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus auxiliis</hi> with what and by what means, and that is <hi>Chyrurgical, Diaetetical</hi> or <hi>Pharmaceutical:</hi> from which three fountains he draws proper Remedies, and applyes fit means for the reduction of Nature to her priſtine and integrity of Operations. And for a copious ſupply of <hi>Pharmaceutick</hi> means; he ſearcheth the <hi>Animal,</hi> the <hi>Vegitable</hi> and <hi>Mineral</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to find out fit matter to work upon; and induſtriouſly applyes himſelf to the <hi>Pyrotechnical</hi> or <hi>Chymical Art,</hi> being the moſt excellent and ingenious way of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal preparations: he is very ſtudious in the Scientifical or Philoſophical part of Chymiſtry (which diſtinguiſheth him from the <hi>Emperick Chymiſt</hi>) contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating the principles and nature of all things in their cauſes and effects; and to prove the verity of his ſpeculative no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; he is very laborious in the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and practical part of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> more
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59336:52"/>particularly deſigning medicinal Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments and tryalls which makes him a perite and moſt excellent <hi>pharmacopoeian,</hi> daily projecting and operating in Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Pharmacy; whereby he adorns the Medicall Art, and enricheth it with a ſtore and treaſury of efficacious and moſt noble Medicines; <hi>Tinctures, Spirits, Eſſences, Elixirs, Extracts, &amp;c.</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mathiolus</hi> well ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>epiſt. ad A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>driam de Blav.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>neminem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum abſolutum eſſe poſſe, imo nê medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crem quidem, qui in Chymia non ſit exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatus.</hi> No Phyſitian can be compleat, ſcarce an indifferent one, that is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in Chymiſtry; and <hi>Sennertus</hi> he is of the ſame opinion, and adds more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over; <hi>Cum enim medicus ſit ille admirabilis,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſ. &amp; diſ. Chym. Cum Galen cap</hi> 18.</note> qui quod eſt divinum in morbis, in medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, in natura novit, actionumque fontes inveſtigat: iſta omnia praecipue Chymiae be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficio aſſequi poteſt:</hi> what ever is rare and extraordinary profound in nature, the knowledge of that is attained chiefly by <hi>Chymiſtry.</hi> And <hi>Meſue</hi> a famous Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian ſpeaks thus of Chymiſts;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antidota. diſtiect</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>they make manifeſt and diſcover the hidden properties of things; that I may confidently ſay, ſcarce any one is able to attaine to the internall knowledge of things, who is not skilfull in Chymicall operations, &amp;c.</hi> To good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59336:53"/>then does the <hi>Hermetic</hi> Phyſitian ſpend his time in Chymiſtry, ſince this is the Key of Knowledge. Wonder not then, but applaude him in the <hi>Spagiricall</hi> diſſecting and opening the bodies of <hi>Concretes,</hi> in ſeparating their <hi>Conſtituent</hi> parts; ſince this is the way to diſcover the hidden properties of each part diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, and to know the reſult of the whole in their natural compoſition. He makes artificial trialls to find out their Similar and diſſimilar natures; their conflicts and actings upon each other, by what repugnant properties they ſtand at diſtance; and by what mediums they are united. He knows how to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the pure from the impure; rightly diſtinguiſhing between this and that <hi>Sulphurious, Saline, Mercurial, &amp;c.</hi> and takes what is proper to ſerve his turn and rejects the reſt. He knows how to tame or kill an exorbitant or noxious qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in a Drug or Minerall, that the ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and excellent medicinal property, may more ſafely and clearly ſhew its <hi>energy.</hi> Tis he alone that knows how to <hi>volatiſe the fixed,</hi> and <hi>to fix the volatile;</hi> that it may ſerve his purpoſe <hi>pro re nata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In learning and knowing theſe and ſuch like artificial operations; the natural
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59336:53"/>Chymiſtry of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> is rightly underſtood; (this art being but an imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature) which being unknown, the art of curing is obſcure and dark; and he ſhoots at randome, that hath not theſe helps to direct and give him aime in the proſecution of any diſeaſe. In the body of man, nature digeſts, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mures, ſeparates, fixeth and volatiſeth, ſubdues and tameth, exalts and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, to make fit for her purpoſe the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimental object, to ſerve her ſeveral uſes, in the nutrition, ſupply and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the body: but when nature is diſordered and put by, or deficient in theſe her daily actions, and theſe her wonted and neceſſary operations; who ſo ſit and who ſo knowing to reſtore them again, as the moſt expert and ſagacious Chymical Phyſitian; whoſe daily buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is to perform theſe operations, that he may the better underſtand the Chymiſtry of Nature, and be able to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt her by his art, where nature is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of her ſelf to perform the work.</p>
               <p>This learned <hi>Spagyriſt</hi> or <hi>Hermetick</hi> Phyſitian does not deſpiſe and throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the laborious Works of our famous Predeceſſors, and wholy ſhake off their Doctrine; but does reſpect, uſe and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59336:54"/>aſſert them, ſo far as is agreeable with the truth of later diſcoveries: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they do him wrong, and have a falſe apprehenſion, that think he practiſeth empyrically with Chymical Medicines, and without Art eſtabliſhed by Rules and Precepts; or by new fantaſtick unſtable notions: no, he ſtands and is founded upon moſt certain Principles, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable by ſenſe; and is able to give the moſt ſatisfactory account of Diſeaſes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Radix and Seminaries; adapting Medicines and exhibiting them moſt rationally and methodically, that he may moſt deſervedly be called <hi>The Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Phyſitian</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>He knows, and can manifeſt it; that the Medicinal Science requires alteration in ſome fundamentals, generally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; that many derivative Doctrines muſt fall to the ground; that the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in this Faculty are not to ſit down &amp; be ſatisfied with the Labours of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors (though worthy to be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced and recorded for their great endeavours) but that there is much work yet left to be finiſhed; and much to be unravelled, that is ſuppoſed perfect: he is therefore ſtrict in the examination of old Tenents, and ſedulous in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploration
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59336:54"/>of truths yet undiſcovered: he is undaunted in the exploſion of errors, though maintained and upheld by many ſucceſſions of the greateſt authorities and profeſſors in this Faculty: he ſtands upon the foundation and principles of nature, diſcovered to him by the <hi>Pyrotechnical Art:</hi> he is not only a ſpeculator of truth; but is trained up in Experimental Philoſophy, and confirms his notions by Chymical practice and ſenſible operations.</p>
               <p>He is thorough-paced in the whole Theory and practice of Phyſick: he has a worthy eſteem for <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> he makes good uſe of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and reads <hi>Galen</hi> to be acquainted with his Doctrine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man of great fame: but above all he magnifies and bottomes himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Van Helmonts Principles;</hi> yet ſwallows not all thats preſented to him by any one; but preſerves himſelf free, and ſuffers not himſelf to be captivated and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced away, but ſticks to his own reaſon and experiments of art, <hi>&amp; nullius addictus jurare in verba magiſtri.</hi> He venerates an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, but is not over ruled and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by a 1000 years practice, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that error bears date ſoon after the creation: authority is no convincing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, but perſwades him to believe,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59336:55"/>where his reaſon cannot clearly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, nor experiment decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, he is well reade in the doctrine of the Schools, and is no ſtranger to the learning of former ages.</p>
               <p>He ſpeaks reverently of Univerſities; as becomes a legitimate ſon of art; and the dignities they beſtow he reſpects in all perſons, being derived from thoſe famous Nurſeries of Literature, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout the world where learning is profeſſed. He is dignified with the <hi>Doctorall</hi> title, <hi>ex meritis</hi> obtained; and labours diligently to adorn his degree with exemplary qualifications, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to the world that this badge and ſignall diſtinction, is not vainly confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and meerly titular; but a reward of vertue, and eminency of parts.</p>
               <p>To conclude, this man is <hi>medicus re &amp; opere;</hi> he is a Phyſitian indeed, <hi>ſuis nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris abſolutus,</hi> accompliſh'd and compleate in the <hi>encyclopaedia medica,</hi> and this is he of whom <hi>Homer</hi> ſpeaks.
<q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<note place="margin">Mener.</note>
                  </q> His greateſt enemy is the <hi>Chymical Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> who uſurping the title of Doctor, and fraudulently perſonating this learned <hi>Chymical Phyſitian;</hi> the ignorance and dangerous practice of the one, redounds
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59336:55"/>to the diſrepute and defamation of the other; becauſe people doe not warily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, and rightly underſtand which is the one, and which is the other: but if you view and compare the characters of both perſons, you may diſcern with half an eye, the vaſt difference between them, and not be deceived for the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="tract">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59336:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> X. <hi>Whether a Phyſitian ought to make his own Medicines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme there are who think it improper; a great indignity and below the title of a <hi>Doctor</hi> to intermeddle with the make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Medicines; and ſuch that doe ſo, are accounted by them mean Phyſitians, of the loweſt rank; and that the eminent reputed Phyſitians ſcorn this way of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, as inferiour to their way of preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and ſending the Patient to their <hi>Apothecary.</hi> But this is an abſurd opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and a great miſtake of the ſimpler ſort of common people: I ſuppoſe the learned and judicious party thinks otherwiſe; and I hope there is no Phyſitian either ſo proud as to deſpiſe a principal part of his profeſſion; or ſo ignorant as to think it was not the ancient cuſtome and generall practice of former ages. <hi>Hypocrates, Galen, Paracelſus, Libavius, Helmont, &amp;c.</hi> the moſt renowned Phyſitians we read of both ancient and modern, were <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoeians,</hi> they were very induſtrious, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and careful in the preparing of their own Medicines; they did not think
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59336:56"/>it a diſhonour to be converſant in making Medicines. Famous <hi>Quercetan</hi> upon this queſtion <hi>an medicine deceat</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? affirmes the ſame:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qutrcetan. rediviv. p.</hi> 218.</note> 
                  <hi>Hypocrates ipſe eorum faciem conſpuiſſet, qui praeparandorum ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum remediorum ſcientiam illi detraxiſſent, quorum utique veteres tam vigiles fuerunt cuſtodes, ut ea nequaquam publica facerent omnibus, ſed magna cautione ſibi aſſeruarent, &amp; filiis ac nepolibus ſeriatim tandem Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitterent, ac per manus traderent.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> (ſays he) would have ſpit in their face, that ſhould detract from him the knowledge of making Medicines, of which our anceſtours have been ſuch vigilant keepers, that in no wiſe they would make them publique, but did preſerve them with great care to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and afterwards did commit them to their Sons and Nephews.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Dr.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vindicia medicin, &amp; medicor. c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Hodges</hi> in that Chapter treating of Practiſing Apothecaries uſurping the Phyſitians function begins thus: <hi>That Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians did originally provide and diſpenſe their own Medicines, will be (I doubt not) eaſily granted by thoſe who are acquainted with the writings of the ancients, wherein it is evident that</hi> Hypocrates, Galen, <hi>and the chiefe Phyſitians as part of their employment prepared what Phyſick they had occaſion to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59336:57"/>ſpend in their practice: and although their ſtrict obligation to conceale their ſacred art, leaſt it ſhould be proſtituted to the rude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of perſons unqualified, might be one argument inclining them (as the moſt likely way for its ſecurity) to confine their buſineſs to their own cloſets and repoſitories; yet I conceive that other reaſons might no leſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their furniſhing themſelves with all neceſſary medicines both ſimple and compound, for theſe hereby very much improved their knowledge in the</hi> materia medica, <hi>ſo that they were not onely able to diſtinguiſh all Plants, Animals and Minerals, and being abroad (if deſtitute of convenient help) readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find but what might ſatisfie the intent in the deſigned cure, but to prepare and compound them till they become apt medicines for their uſe, with all diligence obſerving the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral alterations which hapned in taſte, ſmell or otherwiſe, by which means they were throughly informed, how to change, add, or diminiſh, as there was occaſion, to advance the efficacy of the compoſition; their patients alſo ſhared in the benefit of their induſtry and care herein, who having committed themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of thoſe Phyſitians, looked upon them as the only reſponſible perſons in that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, wherefore they prudently conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their reputation lay at ſtake and the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59336:57"/>lives of their Patients, durſt not intruſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a matter of ſuch concernment to both, but managed all the buſineſs themſelves to a general approbation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis evident that this was the laudable and most rational practice of the Ancients, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the knowledge of Medicines was improved, and the Phyſitian much advantaged by it, and the Patient ſecured. Had it not been the practice of Phyſitians to make their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, how had Medicines arrived to that excellency and worth? not by Preſcription but by the induſtry and experiments of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians in operation.</hi> And what reaſon is there that this ſhould be laid aſide now? That Phyſitians ſhould be Novices? That the <hi>Arcana's</hi> of the Art ſhould be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred and repoſited in the hands of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, alienated from the Profeſſors? This ſeems very ſtrange:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quercet. Rediviv. pag.</hi> 223.</note> take notice what <hi>Quercetan</hi> ſayes; <hi>Quam turpe eſt Medico, ſibi Doctoris titulum arrogare, &amp; materiam qua uti debet, modumque illius parandae ac adminiſtrandae ignorare, patique ſe à miniſtris ſuis ſuperari? an ignoras, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perientiam rerum eſſe magiſtram? Ergo Pharmacopoeius eam callens magiſter erit, tu verò bruta ſtatua Cathedrae affigeris.</hi> You ſee how this great Doctor charges every Phyſitian with the buſineſs of preparing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59336:58"/>Medicines, as a neceſſary duty that lies upon him; which if he neglects how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy he is of his Title and Profeſſion: making of Medicines therefore is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to a Phyſitian, but a credit; he does his duty; it is his ſatisfaction and ſecurity in practice, and a great help to increaſe his knowledge. <hi>Elevat Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici eminentiam &amp; exiſtimationem,
<note place="margin">Chym. in art. form. redact.</note> ſi &amp; manum &amp; mentem adhibeat, ipſeque modum compenendi ſelectiſſima arcana non ſolum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſed &amp; eadem praeparet, praeparataque ipſe communicet:</hi> ſayes <hi>Rolfinc,</hi> it raiſeth the eminency and eſteem of a Phyſitian, if he applyes both his mind and his hand to the compoſing of Medicines.</p>
               <p>But ſome may ſay; there is much ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile work belongs to the making of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, not fit for a <hi>Doctor of Phyſick:</hi> 'tis true, he is not required to toyle in the drudgery of it, that is his ſervants work; but he muſt ſuperviſe, and ſee there be no neglect, miſtake or abuſe: he may have work-men to do the work, but in the interim he muſt be work-maſter, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne the Medicine, to appoint, correct and over-look the whole buſineſs; and where the curioſity, and intrigue of the Art lies, that is to be done by his own hand, that is his Cloſet buſineſs. And
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59336:58"/>truly I cannot ſee how a Phyſitian can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf otherwiſe, if he be not preſent and Superviſor of the Medicine; nor is it reaſonable that a Phyſitian ſhould venter the Life of his Patient, and his own Reputation upon the ſlender care of Servants and raw negligent Boyes, who if you ſtand by them are apt to miſtake and commit errors before your face, as I have too oft obſerved; what negligence is there, and what groſs faults then are committed behind your back? I dare not truſt my own Servants, I ſhould be loth then to truſt another mans. Examples we have had enough of the miſcarriages and miſtakes in medicines, which have coſt too many their Lives; but how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch that never were known is not to be numbred. It is therefore the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians care and duty to have the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Medicine, being principally intereſſed therein; for he that is moſt concerned in a Medicine will be moſt careful and exact: ſome are concerned only in the price of a Medicine; ſo that if a Medicine be ſpecious to the eye thats enough to anſwer his concern; but the Phyſitians concern is in the effects and operation of a Medicine; ſo that he has no way to betray his truſt, but he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59336:59"/>his Reputation, and it is charged upon him. The deſigns of theſe two perſons are very much different; and therefore we may reaſonably judge there is much difference in their Medicines; the one aims and ſtrives to cure, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrives to ſell: an indifferent or bad Medicine may ſell, but ſuch will not Cure.</p>
               <p>View the <hi>Druggiſts</hi> Shop, and you ſhall ſee what great difference there is in the ſame ſpecies of Commodity; ſo that the price is double and more, in the ſame Commodity differing in goodneſs: one ſort being degenerate; of the growth of a Countrey or Climate producing not ſo good; or from a bad ſeaſon of the year; or decayed by age; or damaged by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation and Carriage, or the like: and another ſort is excellent choice ware, and ſcarce: and this variety you will find in moſt, if not all medicinal <hi>Drugs:</hi> yet all is ſold, firſt or laſt; the Shop is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all, and it is turned into Medicine.</p>
               <p>Judge then who it is that buyes the choiceſt and beſt at the double rate; and who buyes the worſt at a cheap and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der rate. That Phyſitian which ſhould buy the worſt to ſave money, is not ſo much a Knave as a Fool, though he is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59336:59"/>both in ſo doing: for he lives by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Cures; by the operation and ſucceſs of a Medicine; not by the price of a Medicine: his profit and advantage ariſeth by the Cure wrought, not by the Medicine ſold: and therefore he will be moſt exact and juſt, in preparing choice Medicines, according to the beſt of his skill, not ſparing pains or coſt, his own intereſt and deſign leads him to it, and I have heard the Druggiſt ſay, ſhould all men be ſo curious in the choice of their Drugs, as ſome few Phyſitians that buy for their own practice, that will have none but the beſt; they could not tell how to manage their Trade; for above the half of their Goods would lie upon their hands: but all are not ſo nice in buying; they have Cuſtomers for the Traſh, which they ſell at low rates, and many chuſe to have of this ſort for the price ſake.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe we are now ſatisfied that the Phyſitians Medicine muſt needs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell all others: he that makes it his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to acquire noble Medicines; that ſpares neither pains nor coſt (as it his intereſt ſo to do) will furniſh himſelf with the choiceſt Medicaments that Art can procure. And indeed, 'tis the glory
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59336:60"/>and pride of a Phyſitian to be furniſhed with a ſtock of excellent Medicines; ſuch as he may confide in; ſuch as he has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated by ſeveral tryals, and gradual alterations, to bring them to the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he aims at; and which he hath oft proved: this man practiſeth boldly, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally and ſecurely: but he that gives an unknown Medicine, is either doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and timorous (as well he may) or elſe he adventures boldly, at hap hazard.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of Phyſitians, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently applying themſelves to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. The one endeavours to get skill in Medicines by reading; the other by practice in making: the firſt depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the traditional account of Authors; the latter upon his own Experiments and Tryals. And here I muſt poſitively aſſert; that bare reading and ſtudying of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, is but imagining of Medicines, a dubious thinking and a deceitful conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, but tryals and experiments in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, is knowledge in medicines. A man cannot be ſaid to be skilful and knowing in Medicines untill he hath made them: you may fancy in your ſtudy by reading, to make and compoſe a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine thus and thus, of ſuch and ſuch Ingredients, after this manner prepared;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59336:60"/>and think you have deſigned an excellent Medicine, that every thing appertaining to it will fall out well, and ſute with the form of the Medicine, as you intend and have imagined: but come to make this Medicine, you will find your ſelf very much miſtaken, either in the proceſs and manner of making, or in the proportion of the Ingredients, or their ſingle corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and due preparations &amp;c. You thought you were very right untill you come to making of it, and then you ſee your errors; ſo that to make this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine as it ought, and to anſwer your aims in it, you muſt at it again, perhaps a third or a fourth time before you hit it right, and make it every way compleat for your purpoſe: now had it not been for theſe tryals and repeated experiments in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, you had never known rightly this Medicine, but had perſiſted in an erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous judgement. This I know to be true by often experience, both in <hi>Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines, which are the moſt difficult.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines how often ſhall you be fruſtrated of your purpoſe, if your own experience in the ſame Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, or collateral experiments do not guide you in the proceſs? How many
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59336:61"/>fallacious proceſſes of Chymical Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are extant in Print? Very many; and many worth nothing when they are rightly made: who ſhall underſtand this? Not the reader of Medicines, but the <hi>Pharmacopoeian,</hi> the expert maker only is a competent judge. You preſcribe a Medicine to be made as your Author di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates to you, who is eſteemed for a learned man, and is ſo: what then? But perhaps this Authour knows as little of the Medicine as your ſelf; he had it by collection from another Author; he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made it, nor perhaps uſed it; but takes it by tradition, as you do from him, and commends it. This is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among Writers: do you think then our knowledge in Phyſick will attain to a perfection after this rate? No, this is not the way, nor does it become a <hi>legal Profeſſor</hi> to proſecute this Courſe, and take up his knowledge upon truſt: but put the caſe, Authors do faithfully and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly deliver the Proceſs of Medicines; yet if you be not an Artiſt you cannot make it; nor can you rightly judge of a Medicine but by the making, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers and unfolds to you the nature of it; you will be then able to determine its uſe, and you will know how to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59336:61"/>and advance its efficacy. I never yet was ſatisfied in, nor pleaſed with a Medicine, untill I had made it halfe a dozen, perhaps half a ſcore times, and each time corrected and altered it, upon examination and obſervation in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated uſe of it: and by ſuch tryals of making, and obſervations in practice and uſe, I did meliorate and improve my Medicines: nor is it poſſible for any man to be knowing and skilful in Medicines, any other way but by practice in their making and uſe. A man may be reading of Medicines ſeven and ſeven years, and yet be unskilful in Medicines. You know Medicines, you ſay, by reading in your ſtudy; I wiſh I could do ſo too; it would ſpare both pains and coſt: but I never could underſtand Medicines as I ought, by reading; and yet I have read over and ſtudied as many <hi>Pharmacopoeians</hi> as you, both <hi>Galenick</hi> and <hi>Chymical:</hi> I ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack'd and conſulted all the Authors I could meet with that treated of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines and Drugs; to inform and acquaint me with variety of Medicines and the beſt wayes of preparation: notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a ground-work, when I came to the making of Medicines, I was but a <hi>Novice,</hi> I committed many errors, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59336:62"/>threw away many medicines, that I had beſtowed much pains about, becauſe they did not pleaſe me, they did not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer my expectation when I had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their operations: but this time ſo employed was not loſt: I found by daily experience and tryals, to gain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; to underſtand the nature of <hi>Drugs</hi> by their ſimple and compound prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, better then all the Books I had read, could teach me. I was ſatisfied then, that my <hi>Book-reading Knowledge</hi> was not comparable to this of <hi>Practice:</hi> that is but the ſhadow and reſemblance of Knowledge; a ſuppoſing and believing things to be ſo; but this is a ſenſible, and certain ſatisfaction to be relyed on far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that of Report and Tradition.</p>
               <p>As it is in <hi>Mechanick Arts,</hi> ſo it is in <hi>Pharmacy:</hi> a man may read of building Ships, ſtately Houſes, making of Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or other curious Engines, many years; but if he be not exerciſed in the making, he will be very much to ſeek and very unready at his firſt undertaking ſuch a work, and ſhall commit many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, untill he be well experienced by conſtant practice: 'tis ſo in Medicines; but you will ſay the building and contrivance of a great Ship, or magnificent Houſe,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59336:62"/>is a far greater work and undertaking then the making of Medicines: I anſwer, no; you are miſtaken, there is more ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, art and pains required, in the deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and making curious Medicines, far above Ships or Houſes, or any other piece of artificial workmanſhip. That man which deſigns and makes Medicines aright, skilfully and exquiſitely, muſt well underſtand that rare Machine of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the fabrick and contrivance of man's body; not only by the eye to know the ſeveral <hi>organical</hi> parts; their due magnitude, figure, number, ſituation, compoſition; but their offices, harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious ſubſerviencies, and all the internal motions and vital operations; then which there is no peece in nature more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: he muſt alſo know the variety of impediments, diſcompoſure, and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this excellent frame, and how to be remedied; and according to this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which is very intricate, muſt he adapt and contrive his Medicines.</p>
               <p>What's a Ship or ſtately Palace to the Body of Man? nothing comparable in the workmanſhip or myſtery of ſupport: now he that makes a Medicine, and is maſter of his Art, hath the <hi>Idea</hi> of this <hi>Microcoſme</hi> in his thoughts, and a true
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59336:63"/>knowledge of all the internal operations; elſe he can never deſign his Medicines to aſſiſt nature this way or that way, and to relieve her in diſtreſs, as he ought. Beſides, the <hi>Materia medica</hi> he uſeth, is far more numerous and various then thoſe materials belonging to any artificial part or rare contrived workmanſhip whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> ſearcheth both <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi> whats <hi>above</hi> and whats <hi>under</hi> the earth, to make medicines of to ſerve his purpoſe, and takes from <hi>animals, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitables and minerals:</hi> and when he hath elected proper and fit matter to work upon, his art and operations upon it are perplexedly difficult, tedious, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfactory before he hath finiſhed and ſatiated his curioſity.</p>
               <p>He that is a true Artiſt in Medicines, that hath an excellent ingeny, and is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious; will not fit down and reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in the common <hi>traditional know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of Medicines, but will be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally buſing himſelf in experiments, reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward and ſtriving to attain excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and more noble medicines, far above the common ſort: and this cannot be brought about, but with indefatigable contrivance and pains in the exerciſe and making of medicines, after long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and manifold tryalls.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:59336:63"/>
               <p>For the <hi>Galenick</hi> Medicines, they are far more eaſie to make, and take up much leſs time; yet no Phyſitian can preſcribe theſe exactly, that is not verſt in making, but muſt referr himſelf to the art of the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> who corrects the preſcription oftentimes as he thinks fit. But groſs and dangerous errors he ſhall commit in preſcribing a Chymical Medicine, that is not a well experienced and practiſed <hi>Chymiſt.</hi> How often are ingredients ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be decocted, that either yield not their vertue to impregnate the <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum;</hi> or elſe evaporate before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction be finiſhed. How often are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients appointed to be diſtilled, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of which, at leaſt their vertuous part intended, comes not into the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but remains in the <hi>retort</hi> or <hi>veſica.</hi> Very often this is ſo, and many errors, which are committed from the inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the preſcriber, a Contemplator of Medicines, no Operator.</p>
               <p>Nor is this all the miſchiefe; for ſince Phyſitians left making their medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, <hi>Apothecaries</hi> began to practice Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; and I think the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> is well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for deſerting the principal part of his profeſſion, and giving it to another. Medicines in ancient times was onely in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59336:64"/>the hands of <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> as the arcana's of art, now they are become a trade, and the <hi>Apothecary</hi> by this cuſtome challengeth them as his due belonging only to him, and thinks himſelf wronged if he have not the whole management of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
               <p>But this is too arrogantly and unduly challenged. The propriety of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines is not yours; but every Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may be his own Pharmacopaeian, and employ his own ſervants in that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs if he pleaſe, nor have you any juſt cauſe to complain of him therein; you have your liberty to follow your trade of ſelling medicines to whomſoever will buy at your ſhops, and that is the intent of your imployment.</p>
               <p>But this does not ſatisfie, you would engroſs the whole buſineſs of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines to your ſelves (which is a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians proper buſineſs) and that Phyſitian who for his own ſatisfaction and ſecurity to his Patients takes upon him the charge and care of Medicines, is ſure to have your badge and by-word, though he be very worthy and able in the Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>And this uſage the Learned Chymical Phyſitian finds; but however he is not diſcouraged from his induſtrious proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59336:64"/>in medicinal experiments and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als to increaſe his knowledge, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the efficacy of medicines by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable labours.</p>
               <p>And truly I muſt affirm, that the beſt Phyſitians in the Nation, are or have been <hi>Pharmacopoeians;</hi> men exerciſed and practiſed in the making of medicines, whereby they become moſt expert Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, moſt knowing and moſt ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: (and this I can make good, if you deſire the proof it) and he that is not well verſt and exerciſed in the practice of <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> is not compleat and fully accompliſhed, but is very uncertain in the adminiſtration and appointment of Medicines, and muſt give place to the <hi>Pharmacopoeian</hi> Phyſitian, who is ſolidly grounded in the knowledge of medicines, which are the inſtruments of Cure.</p>
               <p>And indeed medicines is the grand buſineſs of a Phyſitian; that he had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be defective in any part of his Art, then in this; <hi>Non verbis, ſed herbis:</hi> 'tis medicine that cures, and here muſt be the greateſt care and curioſity in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of excellent medicines, and this cannot be done ſo well as by the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians hand, or under his eye. Who ſo wary and carefull as he whoſe reputation
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59336:65"/>muſt anſwer for the medicine in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs or miſcarriage.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtitutu. l.</hi> 5. <hi>part</hi> 3. 2. <hi>ſect. c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Nemo rectius compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerit medicamenta, quam medicus,</hi> ſays <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertus,</hi>
                  <q>none ſhall compound Medicines better then the Phyſiuan.</q> And in the ſame Chapter he adds: <hi>praeſtantiſſimi medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci domi ſuae ſuis manibus medicament a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerunt, &amp; ſuis nominibus inſigniverunt.</hi>
                  <q>the moſt excellent Phyſitians have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded their Medicines at home with their own hands,</q>
                  <note place="margin">Galen de comp. med.</note> which he proves out of <hi>Galens</hi> writings. Then he brings in <hi>Valeriola,</hi> though ſeemingly of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion, yet cannot deny but the beſt <hi>Phyſitians</hi> in <hi>Galens</hi> time prepared their great <hi>Antidotes</hi> themſelves,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtitut. l.</hi> 5.</note> and accounts it the happineſs of that age. Then ſays <hi>Sennertus, &amp; cur non ſit ſumma felicitas, ſi ea medicamenta, in quibus vita hominum ſita eſt, ipſi etiam medici componant, nec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia non raro indoctis hominibus committen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum;</hi>
                  <q>And why it is not accounted the greateſt felicity, that Phyſitians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould prepare thoſe medicines, in which the life of man is concerned, and not all things committed as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to unlearned men?</q>
               </p>
               <p>A Phyſitians great buſineſs may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into theſe two general parts; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Diſeaſes, and skill in medicines;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59336:65"/>and little remains but is reducible hither: the latter part is as weighty as the firſt; and it as much concerns a Phyſitian, and a duty as incumbent upon him, as any part of his Science, that he ought to be as exact and knowing in this as in that: and how can this be without experience and practice in medicinal preparations? reading will not doe it;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Au. Galen. de alim. fac.</hi>
                  </note> cannot make any one expert: you would be loth to ſaile in that Ship where the Pilot had only read of Navigation; ſo I ſhould be loth to take Phyſick of him that had onely read of Medicines. Perhaps you will ſay, though you do not ſee the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, yet you view it when made, and before it be given: this is not ſufficient knowledge to ſatisfie you or ſecure the Patient; a medicine may be ſpecious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to the eye that you cannot blame, and yet bad enough to him that takes it: a Ship may look very faire and firm to the eye; but the builder alone is able to judge of her; he can tell where ſhe is defective; becauſe he knows every piece of timber, and every plank about her. So is it in Medicines, the maker alone knows whether it be good or bad, by the matter and manner of preparation. I would faine underſtand what true ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59336:66"/>you can make upon the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and effects of an unknown medicine: you appoint ſuch a Medicine and ſuch a Doſe to be given; it works not well, it anſwers not your expectation: you are now at a loſs in your determination; you know not whether you miſſed in the Doſe, or whether the fault be in the Medicine; or diſcordant with this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon only: you know not whom or what to accuſe, <hi>your ſelf</hi> or <hi>the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine or the individuall propriety of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient:</hi> and this difficulty is put upon you becauſe you have no certain knowledge, nor repeated tryalls of the Medicine, and you cannot ſay whether it were a good or a bad Medicine. And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no obſervation from hence. On the contrary, were this Medicine of your own making, in your owne cuſtody, had you proved and tryed it oft, meliorated and improved it by repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed preparations; you might then with much confidence and reaſon give judgement upon its operation, and make a certain obſervation, in this or that caſe, which otherwiſe cannot be done. The diverſity and uncertainty of mens bodies, and peculiar natures, is adventure enough for a Phyſitian
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59336:66"/>to preſume on; and this is unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but I know no reaſon why a Phyſitian ſhould willfully preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on uncertaine and unknowne Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; yea, tis great folly and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, when he may have an aſſured, well grounded, rationall and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiall knowledge, as every Phyſitian ought.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, your imployment is great, you cannot viſit your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients and looke after Medicines too: then ſay I, take no more buſineſſe upon you then you can manage as you ought: that man which hath a full practice for his own perſon it will be ſufficient for him if he be not very covetous and is more in love with mony, then the life of his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents: but eaſe and goodfellowſhip takes up ſo much of ſome mens time, that they cannot perform the whole duty of their imployment.</p>
               <p>Now to reſolve the queſtion; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a duty incumbent uyon the Phyſitian, as moſt rationall, and a part of his profeſſion, to ſuperviſe, prepare, ſafely to keep and have in readineſſe, Medicines for his own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, as a great ſatisfaction to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59336:67"/>and ſecurity to his Patients; judge you.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude with a piece of <hi>Sennertus</hi> who thought the preparation of Medicines very becoming and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the Phyſitian:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sennert. inſtit. c.</hi> 1. <hi>de natura Chyosiae.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Neque etiam praeter dignitatem medici eſſe, componere medicamenta, antiqui illi viri pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimi, medicique peritiſſimi, ſatis docue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt: qui etſi haberent unguentarios, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſiarios, &amp; id genus hominum, qui fucos, unguenta &amp; ſimilia praecipue vendebant, ornando potius quam curando corpori u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilia, totam tamen medicamentorum compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem ipſis non committebant. Ipſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>domi ſuae medicamenta compoſuerunt, neque ſibi dedecori, ſed laudi eſſe duxerunt, ſi rei humano generi vtiiliſſimae operam impende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, neque plus rationis manuum ſuarum quam animi haberent. Imo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>naviorum potius eſſe videtur, omnia miniſtris com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere; quorum vel avaritia, vel impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate factum eſt ſaepius, ut medicaments praeſtantiſsima quae</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>antiqui ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant, vel indoctiſsimis empericis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municarentur, vel corrupta &amp; vitiata a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem ſuam amitterent, nec vires ob quas ab antiquis praedicabantur, amitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="tract">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:59336:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT</hi> XI. <hi>The Excellency of</hi> Chymical <hi>Preparations; compared with</hi> Galenick <hi>Medicines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY the <hi>ignorance</hi> of ſome, and the <hi>knavery</hi> of others, <hi>Chymical</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are a great <hi>bug-bear</hi> with many. Upon the name of a Chymical Medicine, ſome ſtrait conclude it is <hi>Antimony</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> or ſome <hi>poiſonous</hi> or <hi>corroſive</hi> thing, and they are as fraid of it as if it were <hi>Rats-bane.</hi> How this Cheat is put upon the people, and noble brave Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines unjuſtly defamed, we ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: this comes to paſs by theſe means: firſt it ariſeth from ignorant and bold fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows (pretended Artiſts in <hi>Chymiſtry</hi>) who venter upon a ſmall ſtock of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and experience in the Art, to make Medicines of minerals as <hi>Antimony, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, Vitriol, Nitre, &amp;c.</hi> cautiouſly and judiciouſly to be dealt with (by thoſe only who know very well what they do) but being unskilfully and rudely prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; or ignorantly and improperly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are thereby very Churliſh in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of dangerous conſequence ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in their effects. And this raiſeth
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59336:68"/>a cenſure and ſcandal upon all Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Medicines, concluding from hence that they are all ſuch. But what is this to defame <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> and Chymical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; I eaſily grant that ſuch abuſes there are; but what does this reflect on? Not upon the <hi>Art</hi> but the <hi>Artiſt;</hi> not upon Chymical Medicines but the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of them: conſider the perſon who it is, ſee how he is qualified, whether he be a compleat <hi>Chymical Phyſitian:</hi> you will find that ſuch miſcarriages do ariſe from <hi>bold Empericks,</hi> and <hi>Common ſale Medicines;</hi> and if you will venter upon their <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines, or Shop Medicines that you know not from whoſe preparation they were, you muſt take what follows pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, and not unjuſtly defame a moſt excellent Art, and the noble Medicines that are made thereby.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſcattered abroad by vulgar mouths, and objected commonly to us, that Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Medicines are dangerous, which deterr many from the uſe of them, who ſtand in need thereof, and is not reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diable but by ſuch Medicines: but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who they are that give out this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; it is either ſuch as have been abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by cheating Medicines as aforeſaid; or ſuch that underſtand nothing of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59336:68"/>matter; that ſpeak ignorantly by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay and vulgar report, and through ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſneſs are apt to believe and credit it: or elſe if more knowing, are biaſſed by profit, and intereſſed in the adverſe, rigid <hi>Galenick</hi> party, either as Profeſſors thereof, or appertainers to them. But pick out a knowing man not intereſſed in the Profeſſion; as there are <hi>perſons of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi> in this Kingdom that delight in the <hi>Study of Phyſick,</hi> and well underſtand what a <hi>Chymical</hi> and <hi>Galenick</hi> Medicine is: I am confident he will give the right hand and preheminence to <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</hi> Medicines; nor did I ever meet with any ſuch yet, but did prefer the <hi>Chymical</hi> far above the <hi>Galenick</hi> prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Some there are that fooliſhly imagine <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines ſo far to differ from the <hi>Galenick,</hi> as not to be made of the ſame matter with them; but of ſome <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Minerals,</hi> and <hi>venemous Drugs,</hi> that they are afraid ſuch Medicines ſhould come into their bodies: now herein they are much miſtaken, and abuſed in their judgement; for <hi>Chymical</hi> and <hi>Galenick</hi> Medicines are made of the ſame Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients and Drugs, they only differ <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parationis modo,</hi> in the manner of handling
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59336:69"/>and preparing them: but 'tis a hard thing to make ſome doting people believe this; and ſome the more ingenious ſort, are very ſuſpicious of a <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicine <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o nomine.</hi> Dr. <hi>Thomſon</hi> was very ſenſible of this as he declares himſelf in theſe words:
<q>What difficulties ſome of us have undergone to perſwade ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed againſt us (that have imbibed the exitious Precepts of the <hi>Galeniſts</hi>) to admit of thoſe <hi>Chymical</hi> Remedies (when we know they would ſave their lives) is well known to thoſe that have been made ſenſible of their errors here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in:
<note place="margin">Galeno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ale</note> for the very name <hi>Chymical</hi> did ſound ſo deadly in their ears, that many in thoſe places (where we practiſed) did apprehend that he who dealt in ſuch Medicines had a deſign to deſtroy them; and that he was a <hi>Necromancer,</hi> and one that buſied himſelf in ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Art. So far had prevailed the ill reports of ignorance, envy and ſlander, that this moſt laudable Art, and the true profeſſors have ſuffered much, and lie low in the opinion of ſome people: but time will open their eyes that they may fee their error.</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>You ſay <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines are dangerous; ſo is a Sword in a mad
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59336:69"/>man's hand; but when a wiſe man has it, it is his ſafety &amp; defence, becauſe he knows how to uſe it. Some Chymical medicines are more acute and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in operation, and therefore are more cautiouſly to be dealt with, I grant you: therefore take good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions from a Phyſitian that knows well the medicine, being preſent at its operation, and well underſtands for what he gives it you, and then the danger is paſt; elſe any other medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is injurious alſo.</p>
                  <p>You ſay Chymical medicines are dangerous; I ſay 'tis dangerous to be without them; theſe are the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines that muſt help in the time of need; when the nauſeous loading <hi>Drenches, Apozems, Juleps,</hi> and the <hi>Languid Syrups</hi> can do no good: the <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines muſt ſtep in to ſave the man; then a noble <hi>ſpirituous tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> or <hi>rich cordial eſſence,</hi> or <hi>highly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duated Elixir,</hi> that operates briskly, chearfully and friendly with nature, that expands it ſelf in the body <hi>inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneouſly;</hi> raiſeth the drooping ſpirits, inlivens and comforts all the faculties; this is the medicine that gives ſpeedy help to a languiſhing, tyred Patient.</p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:59336:70"/>
                  <p>You ſay <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; I ſay <hi>Galenick</hi> medicines are more dangerous; for, by trifling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the time with ſluggiſh dull medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; many times the opportunity of curing ſlips away, and is not to be recovered by the beſt of medicines, but the Patient muſt die for it. This I have often ſeen; and ſometimes I have known the tyred Patient, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive help and comfort from effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines, that could find none in the other. For Patients to deſert <hi>Galenick</hi> medicines, and have recourſe to the Chymical is common: but to leave the <hi>Chymical</hi> and apply to <hi>Galenick</hi> Phyſick, is very rare. You ſhall hardly meet with a Patient that hath tryed both, but commends <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</hi> medicines above the other; as being much eaſier and pleaſanter to take, as kindly in operation, and more effectual for their purpoſes intended; if a <hi>true Chymical Phyſitian</hi> have had the managing of their ſickneſs.</p>
               </q>
               <p>You ſay <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; and if I ask you wherein, you preſently tell me of <hi>Antimony</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> as if <hi>Chymical Pharmacy</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to theſe <hi>Minerals,</hi> and all <hi>Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:59336:70"/>medicines were <hi>Antimonial</hi> and <hi>Mercurial,</hi> and theſe were the whole <hi>Materia Medica</hi> that a Chymiſt works upon: no, the Chymical Phyſitian is no more bound up to <hi>Antimony</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> then the <hi>Galeniſt</hi> is to <hi>Hellebore, Elaterium</hi> and <hi>Colloquintida,</hi> churliſh Drugs if not well prepared. As for <hi>Antimony</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> (though of good uſe) if theſe were not in nature, the Chymical Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian would be ſufficiently ſupplyed from other Minerals, and out of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Vegetables and Animals, to do his buſineſs. Do you think the Chymiſt does not make as much uſe, and better uſe of all Plants then others? I am ſure he knows them better, will give you a more ſatisfactory account of what he uſeth, then any other that depends on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>Herbal;</hi> that is a <hi>traditional</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, not well examined nor correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but remains full of errors; not is there any firm baſis aſſigned to ground the vertues of thoſe Plants upon, and from which they do aſſurge; but praiſe them for this and for that (many times at random) collected from one Author to another ſucceſſively: but the Chymiſt does anatomize the Plant, ſeparates its parts and will make you ſenſibly diſcern
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59336:71"/>the difference between this Plant and that; diſcovering their ſeveral proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in theſe artificial retextures; then your reaſon being informed by ſenſe, may eaſily judge and certainly determine, for what purpoſe this is for, and what that; and not be beholden or rely upon the dubious reports of Authors, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made ſuch experiments to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the verity of their opinions. But whereas you fall upon <hi>Antimony</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> with a prejudicate opinion as if they deſerved to be baniſhed from me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal employment; you muſt know that theſe Minerals are of good uſe in Phyſick, when an able Artiſt hath the handling of them; but being abuſed by <hi>Bunglers</hi> and <hi>Quacks,</hi> theſe Minerals lie under a reproach.</p>
               <p>You ſay <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and therefore they are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be taken by drops and grains; elſe they might be given in a larger quantity as <hi>Galenick</hi> medicines are, half a pint, or a pint at a Doſe. Here is a fallacious ſcandal; you call that dangerous, which is only of great power and efficacy, that is acute and brisk in operation; that is reduced to a ſmall quantity for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and eaſe of the Patient; that a drop
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59336:71"/>compriſeth as much vertue, as a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of another medicine: 'Tis true, theſe Medicines are not to be played with, as Children lick <hi>Syrup;</hi> but diſcreetly to be uſed: and therefore if a <hi>Chymical</hi> medicine be ſaid to be dangerous, it is not ſo <hi>in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> natura,</hi> but <hi>in uſu malo;</hi> not in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the imprudent uſe and abuſe of it. 'Tis dangerous for Children to play with knifes; but when Wiſe men uſe them, there is no danger: ſo the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a Chymical Medicine is in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful, careleſs uſe of it: dangerous in the hands of fools, and received from the hands of ſuch; but prudently taken from the hands of a Phyſitian that knowes the preparation of the medicine, none is more ſafe; none ſo ſafe, becauſe they ſurpaſs all other in amicable operation and good effects.</p>
               <p>Chymical Medicines, you ſay, are not ſo mild and gentle as the <hi>Galenick,</hi> which are more familiar to Nature, and may more freely be uſed: But the <hi>Chymical</hi> is not to be uſed but upon extraordinary occaſions, and deſperate caſes; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Proverb, <hi>A deſperate Diſeaſe muſt have a deſperate Remedy.</hi> I anſwer, You are much miſtaken in your Opinion and Cenſure: Medicines <hi>Chymically</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59336:72"/>by a true <hi>Philoſophical Artiſt and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Phyſitian,</hi> are as gentle and benigne in their operation as any Medicines in the World; and if it happen otherwiſe, it does ariſe from the inſufficiency of the Artiſt, or the imprudence of the Patient: And ſuch miſcarriages as theſe happen in the Galenick Practice, and is common to Galenick Medicines as oft as Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal: But caſt your Eye upon both ſorts of Medicines, prepared according to the rules of either Art, and the beſt <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoeia's</hi> of both Sects; and you may pick out as churliſh medicines in the one as the other. I ſhall not defend all Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Medicines that ſtand upon Record in Chymical Authors; and you I think will not juſtifie all the <hi>Galenick;</hi> but have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to one that is <hi>Chymiatros <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a true Chymical Phyſitian, Judicious and Expert in Chymical Pharmacy;</hi> he will produce you ſuch Medicines of his own preparation, that you may confide in, for the grand purpoſes and intentions of Cure, <hi>Emetick, Cathartick, Diaphoretick, Diuretick, Cardiack,</hi> &amp;c. as nothing can operate with more facility and amicably with Nature, in her weakeſt Condition, and in the tendereſt age: and therefore not in deſperate caſes onely, but in all
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59336:72"/>caſes the <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines are of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe; benigne and friendly to Nature, various in their Kinds as well vegetable and Animal, as Mineral; ſo that the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Phyſitian</hi> hath his choice to appoint, this or that <hi>pro re nata</hi> as the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: Moreover, herein lies the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> that it can tame the greateſt Poyſon, and make it good Medicament, if there be occaſion for it: Herein lyes the Excellency of <hi>Chymicall</hi> preparation, that the faeculent droſſie part is ſeparated from the pure and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous; the excelling parts are drawn forth and preſerved, the inutile and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſeful are rejected and ſequeſtred. Hence the noble <hi>tinctures, and reviving Elixera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Spirits and Eſſences</hi> are drawn: the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of all things is commanded by the skilful <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> and none but he ſearcheth the Treaſury of Nature. Is there any thing good in Nature attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that he cannot acquire and poſſeſs? Is there any thing ſo bad that he cannot correct and alter? If not he, then no man.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Primroſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Primroſe de Vulg. Err. li.</hi> 4. <hi>ca</hi> 1.</note> though a Friend to the <hi>Galenick</hi> method and practice; yet in his Book of <hi>Vulgar Errors,</hi> takes notice of the unjuſt Cenſure that Common People
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59336:73"/>paſſe upon <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines; <hi>Additae igitur fuerunt operationes Chymicae, ad aegro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolatium, artis decus et ornatum, non quidem abſolutè, ſed ut melius et commodius Medici Mederentur. Quaedam tamen deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent plurimos aegrotantes ab horum remedio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum uſu: Primum eſt quod putent omnia Chymicorum remedia eſſe valentiſsima, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare ſtatim vel occidere, et eſse remedia, ut vocant, deſperata, citò quidem &amp; jucunde opus ſuum perficere, ſed minus tutò, et quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam post ſeſe labem in viſceribus relinquere, quae nunquam, aut vix poſtea eluatur. Satius autem eſse putant, tardiùs Curari, modo tuta et ſecura ſanitas ſuccedat; ſat citò, inquit proverbium, ſi ſat bene. Verum haec en ignorantiâ iſtius artis originem habent, et quorundam nebulonum audaciâ, qui ſolum vehementiſsimis utuntur, et praepoſtera ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione praeparatis, non enim quaelibet Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica praeparatio cuilibet Medicamento con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit, Mercurio dulci utimur innoxiè, codem ſublimato aut praecipitato, non niſi cum vitae diſcrimine. Plurima enim habent Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Medicamenta valde benigne, minimum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> violenta: eadem ſiquidem eſt materia medica Pharmacopoei Chymici et vulgaris, ex ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getabilibus, animalibus, mineralibus et omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tam benignis quam violentis, quae in uſum medicum venire ſolent. Praeparatio
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59336:73"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utem Chymica in violentis quae noxia ſunt, emendat, aut tollit, ſecuriora ea gratioraque efficit: Quin etiam Cardiaca et roborantia habent Chymici quam plurima, vulgaribus ſaepe elegantiora.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Author though a <hi>Galeniſt</hi> in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Method of Practice;
<note place="margin">Eodem Cap.</note> yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines to be the moſt excellent, moſt pleaſant, and very ſafe; <hi>Cum igitur Medici Officium ſit ut citò, tutò, jucundè curet, hand dubiè id melius faciet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructus Chymicis Medicamentis, quorum efficacia major, et praeparationis elegantia ad jucunditatem faciunt.</hi> Here he ſaith, for ſpeed, ſafety and pleaſantneſs of Curing, the Chymical Phyſitian is beſt accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But the very name <hi>Chymical,</hi> is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate word, and imports ſtrange things in the Opinion of ſome people, which affrights them from all medicines that bear that denomination: Truly if I knew any ſuch concealed miſchief under it, as you do imagine, I ſhould be as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to inform you, as now to convince you of your error; and to warn you of it, as now to remove that prejudice and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which you unjuſtly conceive and harbour; were Chymical Medicines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate Phyſick as you imagine, ſo many
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59336:74"/>famous Phyſitians would not have uſed them, nor ſtood up for them: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Hypocrates</hi> nor <hi>Galen</hi> was not ſo happy as to be acquainted with theſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; yet their Diſciples that embrace their doctrine and precepts, applaud and uſe <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crato</hi> Phyſitian to 3.
<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſil. à Schol. Edit.</note> Emperours, very much commends <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines, and profeſſeth to uſe them. And <hi>Eraſtus</hi> though a great <hi>Anti-Paracelſian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In praefat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>per. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paracelſitor.</note> confeſſeth he does not diſapprove of the <hi>Chymical</hi> preparation of Phyſick, but praiſeth and approves it. <hi>Greg. Horſtius Fernelius, Heurnius,</hi> theſe Worthy Authors (ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and followed by all the <hi>Galeniſts</hi>) do the like. And <hi>Sennertus</hi> a moderate man, endeavouring to reconcile theſe two grand diſſenting parties, gives the preheminence to <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines; but allowes of both in the practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to be of good uſe. And <hi>Maebius</hi> a late Writer and favourer of <hi>Galenick</hi> Doctrine, ſpeaking of the ſeveral ſects of Phyſitians, makes ſome Exceptions againſt <hi>Chymical</hi> Principles, but the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> medicines, he cannot but extoll and confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">Fundament. Medicin.</note> 
                  <hi>In praeparatione Medicamento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tamen palmam veterum Medicinae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt.</hi>
                  <q>But in the preparation of medicines (ſayes he) the Chymiſts win the Garland.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:59336:74"/>
               <p>Many ſuch teſtimonies as theſe I might give concerning Chymicall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines of their efficacy and ſafety from very approved Authors of the <hi>Galeniſts:</hi> I ſuppoſe now you will entertain a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion of <hi>Chymicall</hi> medicines; you will not think them dangerous, having the approbation of ſo many learned men and the moſt eminent Phyſitians of the <hi>Galenic</hi> party (to let paſs the teſtimony of the moſt experienced Doctors and Operators in Chymiſtry) and indeed there is ſcarce any Phyſitian of known parts now, but doe freely admit of and practice with Chymicall medicines; and very oft you take <hi>Chymicall</hi> preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons though preſcribed by a Galenic Doctor, and coming out of an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> ſhop; which you doe not perceive, becauſe admixed with <hi>Galenick</hi> Phyſick: and if you can take <hi>Chymicall</hi> Phyſick at this rate, when the Phyſitian hath not been privy to the preparation, nor the <hi>Apothecary;</hi> but bought of ſome Shop Chymiſt or other whoſe honeſty and care they truſt; you may with great confidence then take them from the hands of a <hi>Chymicall</hi> Phyſitian and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Operator; whoſe great buſineſs it is to prepare choice medicines for his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59336:75"/>own practice, with great care and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs, for his reputation is ingaged for every default, nor can he ſhift it off and throw it upon another, becauſe he undertakes the whole work. Nor does he aime at the ſale of medicines herein, but to effect difficult cures, and to be ſatisfied in the curioſity of medicines which puts him upon this trouble for the good of his Patients; and therefore I need ſay no more of his medicines; nor anſwer farther to cleare this objection againſt Chymicall medicines, that they are dangerous:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sennert. conſ. &amp; diſ. Chym. cum Galen. c.</hi> 18.</note> only remember what <hi>Sennertus</hi> ſays, <hi>intereſt multum in Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis medicamentis, quis ca praeparavit,</hi>
                  <q>it behoves you to know well the artiſt that prepares them;</q> and being given by a skilfull hand you need not feare the uſe of them; but expect as much then as Art and Medicine can perform.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Chymicall</hi> medicines ſome ſay are a new invention, and therefore not to be eſteemed equall with the old <hi>Galenick</hi> medicines.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Antiquity or novelty is no ſufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove the goodneſs of one thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove another, except in Theological truths.</hi> But in Phyloſophical, if either invites to adhere, I ſhould think new inventions
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59336:75"/>might more perſwade, upon the ſcore of reaſon, to be embraced and followed then the old: but underſtand what I meane by new inventions; not the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of light roving wits, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of giddybrains affecting novelties; but the ſolid inventions and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of judicious Artiſts, ſufficiently experimented and approved. Looke back upon all arts and ſciences in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, and you will ſee how rude and inartificiall they were then to what they are now; how polite and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite now, how much compleated, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſings and additions, to what they were formerly in their rough draughts: you will then be convinced that the later in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and contrivances by learned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious men, doe far exceed the firſt exemplars; and that arts and ſciences are daily improved by new additions and ingenious alterations. And it were a ſhame to us if it were not ſo: ſhall other men in all ages have their inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and not we ours? why muſt we be tyed up from invention? I doe not ſee a perfection yet: there is a <hi>plus ultra:</hi> had there been ſuch a reſtraint and check upon our Predeceſſors (to be derided for ſick-brain noveliſts and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59336:76"/>Innovators) and they timorouſly had ſtood in awe of the raſh Cenſure of fooliſh or envious people; where had all our knowledg been? we now ſhould be groaping in the darkneſs of Error and Ignorance, wanting their Labours and Lights; and we had now been but lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a foundation in Arts and Sciences, whereas (thanks to the great Endeavors and Ingenious Improvements and Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Learned Men in their ſeveral Ages) we are now upon Ornament, and the finiſhing part, in moſt of them; and the hardeſt knotty work is paſt.</p>
               <p>But I have not done with this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yet: You ſay <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines are <hi>Novel</hi> Inventions; What then? Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is not perfected yet; there is room enough for invention: there is a great deal to be corrected and altered, and there is much to be added before the Art be compleat. Pertinent to this point we are upon,
<note place="margin">Sennert. Conſ. et diff. Chym. cum Gal.</note> is that place of <hi>Sennertus,</hi> where he ſaith,
<q>The Antiquity alone of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon medicines does not detract from the Chymical in the leaſt, nor is the Chymical for their Novelty to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted inferior to the Galenical. 'Tis a fooliſh thing to eat Acorns, when we have gotten good Corn; And who now
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59336:76"/>does not uſe printed Books which the Antients wanted, and yet were learned.</q> And they themſelves, which deſpiſe <hi>Chymical</hi> medicines for their <hi>novelty</hi> do uſe <hi>Rhubarb, Mechoacan, Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Guajacum, Saſſafras, Sarſaperilla, Bezoar ſtone,</hi> and many more which were unknown to <hi>Hypocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen.</hi> And they which lived before <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Galens</hi> time, lived well alſo: notwithſtanding therefore the works of <hi>Hypocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> are not to be thrown away. How many moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable obſervations of learned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians are now extant? alſo how many the beſt compoſitions of Medicines, which were unknown in the time of <hi>Hypocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> with which now the art of Phyſick is much adorned? all things have their beginnings, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and perfection: and nothing is invented and perfected at one time. And therefore it is our parts to labour, not only to defend the inventions of the Antients, but alſo as much as in us lies to proſecute thoſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, to enlarge and bring them to perfection. And therefore Antiquity alone is not ſufficient to preferr the Common Medicines above the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:59336:77"/>
               <p>You have the opinion of this learned man, a moderator between the <hi>Galeniſt</hi> and the <hi>Chymical</hi> Phyſitian; and he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines very juſtly, that Antiquity does not give the prehemince to <hi>Galenick</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; but rather that it ſhould give place to later diſcoveries of Medicines; theſe being the Reviſes, Compleatments and mature productions of Art; much to be preferred before the antiquated Medicines; being but rude experiments, and an induction only to greater and more artificial operations and tryals.</p>
               <p>But I have heard ſome Phyſitians ſay, that they preſcribe no medicine but what has been tryed and uſed 500 or a 1000 years: and except you bring the authority of ſo many years, a medicine is not eſteemed nor hardly allowed by ſuch: truly, I like their medicines never the better for their antiquity, but the worſe: not therefore, deſpiſing antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; but therefore, becauſe their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines were unpoliſhed, rude and chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, to what they are now. Our ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional way of correction and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of medicines, does far ſurpaſs the Ancients. They went upon experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments altogether at firſt; and thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments were not to be called rational
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59336:77"/>as ours now, but at a venter: for they had not <hi>Analogy</hi> to direct them. But it is not ſo with us now; and therefore our experiments and inventions are guided by ſtrong reaſon and collateral experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and we are able to ſet a <hi>probatum eſt</hi> to any new medicine, to give it credit in the world after ſatisfaction from our own tryals of uſe; and it is as authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick as a thouſand years practice, in the judgement and opinion of knowing men; that can compare the maturity of our knowledge in theſe later dayes, with their indigeſted notions of former ages.</p>
               <p>You ſay you preſcribe no Medicine but of a thouſand years ſtanding: if any one ſhould ſay I uſed any Medicine of a thouſand years ſtanding (not corrected and altered) I ſhould take it as a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement: but you think it is a ſafe way of practice, to have the authority of a thouſand years to back you, much good may it doe you, <hi>per me licet;</hi> but I ſhall uſe none of your old Medicines. Truly I am ſo far from adhering to old medicines, that I may ſay, every year I practice with new medicines; that is in part; not wholy new, but altered, corrected and improved: and by ſuch tryalls of preparation and alteration,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59336:78"/>medicines gradually receive their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the Artiſt a more exact know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>But ſome may object; if you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually altering of medicines, what cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty is there in your medicines, when you are always upon experiments and changing? to this I anſwer; much cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty I find and ſatisfaction in theſe try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of alteration; for thereby I fully underſtand what my medicine is and the nature of all the ingredients are better diſcovered: I ſee how to correct, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and each time to advance a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to a greater perfection and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of operation. He is no Artiſt that either bounds himſelf within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of any author, or wants ingeny to improve and meliorate his firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance and invention of medicine.</p>
               <p>It is in medicines, as in all other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial works and inventions: let an artiſt deſign any piece of work, when he has made it, and ſurveys the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it in all its parts; though it be well and ingeniouſly done, yet he ſees where it might be mended; <hi>Secundae cogitationes ſunt meliores;</hi> and when he comes to make it a ſecond time, and a third; he will not make it as it was at
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59336:78"/>firſt, but he alters and varies much; his Fancy is ſtill working to give it greater perfection, to make it more advantagious and commodious for the purpoſes inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Shall any one blame this Man, and accuſe him with levity and uncertainty, for giving liberty to his Invention and rational contrivance, dictated to him by the reviſing of his former Labours? Will any one ſay, This man goes upon uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Experiments and Alterations? No, he works more certainly the ſecond time, then the firſt; and third more certain then the ſecond: he ſees a fault and mends it the next time; he ſees where his firſt inventions failed him; he finds by the uſe and daily tryal of it, where and how to make it more fit, uſeful and exact for the purpoſe the next time: So that Induſtry and Time makes new diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries and inventions to give every thing a greater excellency and worth, and thus have all Arts and artificial works encreaſed and improved, by the ingenious inventions and additional Contrivances of Induſtrious men, ſucceſſively in all Ages: But they that lazily dote upon Antiquity; fooliſhly or wilfully ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Copies to be perfect, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires nothing but our imitation; have
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59336:79"/>gotten a fair pretence to be drones, and live upon other mens labour.</p>
               <p>He is not ſo much a Doctor of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick as a Scholar in Phyſick, that practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth altogether by the Book; that dare not truſt his own Abilities, but muſt have the precept or example of an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to follow, and tye himſelf up to a Pattern, that he dare not alter: He that is a Compleat Artiſt, that hath the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> and Reaſon of the Art grounded in him by <hi>Study and Practice,</hi> he is able and ſufficient to manage and contrive his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, if all Books were burnt: But do not miſtake me, as if I ſlighted Books and Authors; they preſerve Learning and Arts alive from one Generation to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, elſe they would dye and wither away: And by theſe helps we have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to what Learning and Ingenuity we now call our own; for which I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the memorable worth of them. But, being once made maſters of their works, ſufficiently grounded and exerciſed in any Art: Such a man then is his own guide, he is ſwayed by nothing but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Experience; that's the Baſis and Principles that he is grounded on; Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority prevails not with him, he is able then to contradict the greateſt repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59336:79"/>authority that hath gone before him.</p>
               <p>When firſt I came acquainted with Dr. <hi>Starky (an Expert Chymiſt)</hi> and finding him a very acute <hi>Philoſopher</hi> and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced <hi>Phyſitian;</hi> I had a deſire to ſee his Library, and what Authors he converſed with: In his Chamber there lay <hi>Van Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monts Works,</hi> and 2. or 3. ſmall Books, which was all that ever I ſaw, or that he owned to have. Upon Conference afterwards and more intimate Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, we fell upon diſcourſe of <hi>Phyſical Writers and Chymical Pharmacopoeia's;</hi> and as I remember, the reſult of his diſcourſe was to this purpoſe; <hi>That to initiate and ground a Phyſitian in the ſtudy and practice of Phyſick, thoſe helps were neceſſary to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and guide him, untill he had acquired ſuch a Knowledge and Experience, as made him maſter of his Art: Then he is no longer under the tutorage of Authors, but relyes upon his own Reaſon and Experiments; he is then able to correct Authors, and find out their failings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I queſtion not but he had read as many Books as other men, to ſatisfy his Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and had ſuckt the marrow out of the beſt; had fortified his own Reaſon, and laid a good foundation within himſelf, by
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:59336:80"/>Practice and Experiments; did then ſtand upon his own leggs, had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to this or that Author, but was able to reſolve himſelf in difficult caſes; by the <hi>Analogy</hi> of his own Experiments, and ſtrength of his own reaſon; was then a Tutor and Guide to himſelf; able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed and make a fair progreſs, where other men ſate down, as their <hi>ne plus ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> being the utmoſt extent of their Book information, and farther they cannot go: but this Artiſt was continually upon projection and invention of Medicinal preparations, and he had a very ſubtle head for that purpoſe: he relyed not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Authors in the proceſs of his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, but his own reaſon and the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> of former tryals, lead him from one experiment to another. And thus does the Philoſophical ingenious Artiſt, who is <hi>adeptus,</hi> is alſo <hi>adeſpotus,</hi> or he is but a dull <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> that can proceed no farther then his Book teacheth.</p>
               <p>But to my purpoſe, from whence diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe hath led me: You ſay, <hi>Chymical</hi> Medicines are <hi>Novell</hi> Inventions: That I deny, except you call <hi>Novelties</hi> of 2000 years ſtanding, as it may be proved from the Writings of credible Authors. And what if Chymiſtry were a new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59336:80"/>that would not derogate from the Excellency and worth of it;
<note place="margin">Sennert. Conſ. et diſſ. Chym. cum Gal.</note> as <hi>Sennertus</hi> ſayes, <hi>Licet hodiè primùm Chymia inventa eſſet; dignitati tamen ejus id nihil detrahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret: Sat enim antiquum quod ſat bonum: nihil<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> invenire eſt quod non aliquando no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum fuerit; et multa pro novis habentur, quae ſunt antiquiſſima.</hi> But <hi>Chymical</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines ſtand upon a very ancient founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the profeſſors thereof have been Men renowned in their Generations, and famous to all poſterity. But were there not that Antiquity to plead for them; yet the Experience of later times, the proofs and tryals which have been made in our own times, of theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Medicines, what they have done, when others have failed; (of which we are witneſſes and can atteſt) are ſufficient to give a confidence in and relyance upon them, as the moſt pleaſant, efficacious and wholeſome Medicines in the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="tract">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:59336:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TRACT.</hi> XII. <hi>The Vertues of</hi> Catholick, Specifick <hi>and</hi> Appropriate <hi>Medicines examined; and compared with each other, in their Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, Safety and Certainty of Operation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Amongſt the Writings of ſome Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Phyſitians and the beſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, both Ancient and Modern, we find them to make mention of, and to diſtinguiſh Medicines by theſe Titles of <hi>Catholick, Specifick</hi> and <hi>Appropriate:</hi> and therefore I think it worthy of our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and debate, rightly to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the verity and reaſon of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, and the advantages that it may afford us by a due examination. And the rather, becauſe the <hi>Catholick</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine hath been much abuſed by ſome Pretenders of mean abilities; is thereby defamed, and become diſ-eſteemed and ſlighted in the opinion and acceptance of the People.</p>
               <p>moſt pet here are that wholly deny any ſuch thing in Nature or Art, as a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Univerſal</hi> Medicine: Others plead very high for it; and thoſe, Men of no
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:59336:81"/>ſmall account, but of great Learning and Reputation in the World. But to wave the Authorities of Famous Men on both ſides, we will dive into the reaſon and probability of the thing, and prove it that way; as being more prevalent and more ſatisfactory, then the Reports and Teſtimonies of Authors affirming it. And firſt I ſhall lay open the tearms, and ſhew you what is meant by <hi>Catholick, Specifick,</hi> and <hi>Appropriate</hi> Medicines. <hi>Catholick</hi> is Univerſal, and in the full latitude and extent of the word, a Medicine curing all Diſeaſes in all perſons is ſignified thereby, and ſo underſtood by many: A <hi>Specifick</hi> Medicine is proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar for the Cure of one diſeaſe onely, and in all perſons. An <hi>Appropriate</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is narrower then that, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained; being adapted to one indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall perſon, for this or that Diſeaſe or complicated Diſeaſes, deſigned for his caſe alone, and not fit for another. But Catholick is not to be taken in the largeſt ſenſe before named, when I aſſert the <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine; nor is it the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and intent of the moſt ſolid and grave Writers; that ſtand up for the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine: But by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> is underſtood by them, (and it is
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59336:82"/>my own ſenſe) <hi>Medicamentum Poluchre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton;</hi> a Medicine of a general uſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in various caſes and in divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; ſo that Catholick or Univerſal is not meant <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> and is reſtrained to ſome general inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Cure uſeful in divers caſes and diſeaſes; and for diſtinction ſake, to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference this more general Medicine from the <hi>Specifick</hi> and <hi>Appropriate,</hi> that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained and limited in their power to particular caſes and perſons. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Medicine may be called <hi>Catholick,</hi> though it do not cure all diſeaſes; yet may be of neceſſray uſe in all diſeaſes: as ſuch a Medicine that fortifies Nature <hi>radically</hi> in her principles (being well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned and curiouſly prepared) that gives aſſiſtance and ſtrength to all the faculties; ſuch a Medicine is <hi>Catholick</hi> and of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral uſe, and may very profitably be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in all declenſions, and ſtruglings of Nature contending with any diſeaſe, be it this or that: Nor does this Medicine undertake the whole Cure and exclude the uſe of other Medicines, though it be a Catholick Medicine. But other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines (and Catholick alſo) may come in and bear their part in the Cure, as the skilful Phyſitian ſhall appoint and think
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:59336:82"/>fit in their due courſe and order. And therefore you are not to think that there is but one <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine, but a plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of them is allowed, and that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally according to our preſent ſenſe and meaning. In Purgation, that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine which cleanſeth the Body of all impurity and ſuperfluous humours, be they of this fort or that ſort; that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth Nature of all noxious matter that reſides in thoſe parts to be carried off this way; working ſo, not onely in one body but divers, of various and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent diſeaſes, performing its operation with facility, eaſe and gentleneſs; this Medicine is Catholick, and may be enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled univerſal in this Claſſis of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe in tranſpiration; ſuch a Medicine as excites the <hi>Archaeus</hi> to a more vigorous action; that puts the bloud up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fermentation and ſeparation of any impure <hi>heterogene</hi> admixture, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigorates the expulſive faculty; that opens the pores of the body, and penetrates through all the parts, breathing out and diſ-lodging degenerate ſtinking humors; that is Balſamick, reſiſts corruption, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies and ſweetens the body: and all this by a friendly <hi>Diaphoretick</hi> operation in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:59336:83"/>divers Bodies, differently affected and degenerated; and yet ſucceſsfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed withall; (at leaſt ſo much as can be expected in the power of Medicine; conſidering the capacities of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) this may deſervedly be called a <hi>Univerſal Diaphoretick</hi> Medicine: and ſuch <hi>Catholick</hi> or general Medicines as theſe, are attainable by art and diligent labour in Medicinal Preparations; and theſe are the moſt excellent, ſafe and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Medicines: And to prove what I have ſaid, That there are ſuch Medicines as I have now deciphered, I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them of my own preparation, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the incredulous.</p>
               <p>You ſee now what is meant by a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Medicine; at leaſt what is my meaning in the tearm: and a Catholick Medicine thus underſtood and ſo limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is the Medicine I ground my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on, and make compariſon with the Specifick and Appropriate Medicines; whether is more ſafe, more certain of operation, and efficacious in curing; the true Catholick Medicine, or the Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and Appropriate, that is particularly deſigned and appointed for each perſon and different caſe.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:59336:83"/>
               <p>To manifeſt the rational deſignment of <hi>Catholick Medicines,</hi> and to ſhew you upon what grounds and conſiderations the true <hi>Philoſophical</hi> Artiſt does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive and perfect them; take notice that he well knows &amp; conſiders the body of Man, and all the internal operations ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to each other in a ſtate of ſanity and health: he conſiders alſo the functions of the body diſordered and depraved; the digeſtions vitiated and weak; (the ſprings of moſt diſeaſes, from whence the vital ſtreams are impure and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.) He determines aright concerning the <hi>Archoeus,</hi> as <hi>dominus fac totum</hi> in the oeconomy and government of the body; how to be fortified when weak and feeble, how to be pacified and calmed when furious, raging and extravagant. He conſiders how many wayes Nature hath to help her ſelf in the diſcharge of any morbifick matter; <hi>per vomitum, per aluum, per ductus urinarios, per cutis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros.</hi> From ſuch conſiderations as theſe, as general Rules and Directions, the Rational Phyſitian propoſeth certain ſcopes and intentions to be aimed at in the deſigning of his <hi>Catholick Medicines</hi> without reſpect to this or that <hi>indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um,</hi> but levelling at the ſpecifick na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man's body.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:59336:84"/>
               <p>And for a proſecution of theſe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he electeth ſuch and ſuch Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients proper for theſe ſeveral opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; he corrects, prepares and fits them, operates upon them according to Art, and forms them into ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Medicines, anſwering the ſeveral purpoſes aforeſaid. He tries them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral perſons, and different caſes; (but requiring the ſame manner of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whether it be purging, ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, provoking Urine, Anodine, or the like.) They do not pleaſe him at firſt, becauſe they work variouſly and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, diſcordantly with ſome bodies: he then begins to caſt about in his mind, where the faults may be in ſuch a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine; whether in the matter, or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of preparation: and thus by examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of each particular, how congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, how effectual and operative, how amicable ſuch and ſuch Ingredients are, being ſo corrected and prepared; and by this <hi>projection</hi> and <hi>ſcrutiny;</hi> he begins to ſee where and how theſe medicines may be mended,
<note place="margin">Nihil eſt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum ac perfectum.</note> and altered for the better. He falls to work again, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triues a better way, and perhaps better Drugs, more fit and excellent for theſe purpoſes; as time and experience by
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59336:84"/>tryals will dictate to him. And now he makes them more artificially, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves his Medicines, taking out and putting in, and variouſly altering as his ingenuity and reaſon doth prompt him. He uſeth and tryes them again and again, in ſeveral caſes; and thus continues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and making, untill by length of time and conſtant endeavors, he advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth theſe Medicines to be radicall and univerſal; that they ſhall perform their ſeveral diſtinct operations, in divers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and different diſeaſes, with great facility and advantage to all, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſuch an operation in their Cures.</p>
               <p>Now you ſee what a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is, how deſigned and contrived, and how it gains the deſired perfection of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality: Let us now compare this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine with the <hi>Specifick</hi> and <hi>Appropriate,</hi> and then you ſhall judge whether is more ſafe, certain, and effectual in curing.</p>
               <p>Some ſtand up for <hi>Specifick</hi> Medicines peculiar for every diſeaſe, and proper for that only; and theſe ſay they are the the brave Medicines: I do not deny the bounty of Nature, in affording variety of <hi>Specificks;</hi> that there may be ſuch in Nature; but the difficulty and uncertainty is in finding them out: for
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59336:85"/>thoſe Medicines ſo accounted, we find them to ſail and deceive our expectation oftentimes, as others do; and therefore they are either not rightly known, or not well uſed. Beſides what every Phyſitian finds in his own practice daily; we read in ſeveral Authors publiſhing their own <hi>Therapeutick</hi> Experiments; how many Specificks ſo accounted, they have given in ſeveral Diſeaſes that have taken no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: one commends one thing, another prefers another in the ſame diſeaſe: and the ſame Specifick given to one with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, hath been given to another without any benefit. And this uncertainty not my own experience only urges; but alſo the reports and relations of credible Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors in the hiſtory of their Cures do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it.</p>
               <p>I do not ſpeak this to leſſen the bounty and goodneſs of Nature; or to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage an induſtrious Enquirer from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing after the knowledg of <hi>Specificks,</hi> but untill we be better ſatisfied in them, let us value the true <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine as moſt certain to rely upon, becauſe we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from it what is manifeſt in it, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently proved.</p>
               <p>But farther; in granting your Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Medicines for every diſeaſe, there is
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59336:85"/>ſome difficulty in the admiſſion according to the common acceptation of <hi>Specificks</hi> and <hi>Appropriate</hi> Medicines: for admit there be a Plant proper for every diſeaſe, which you call Specificks; yet how are theſe <hi>Specificks</hi> fit for every <hi>individuum,</hi> that hath ſuch a diſeaſe? Here you muſt allow of their <hi>Protean</hi> nature to vary and agree with every <hi>individual Propriety:</hi> or you muſt deny the neceſſity of Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priating Medicines to every ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: or you muſt acknowledg theſe <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificks</hi> to work congruouſly and generally as <hi>Univerſals,</hi> ſo as to apply fitly to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>individuum,</hi> and then they are <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Medicines.</p>
               <p>Now concerning Appropriate Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which are adapted <hi>pro re nata</hi> for every particular caſe; we will enquire into their worth and certainty of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what may be expected from their peculiar appointment, above what a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Medicine is likely to effect. And here I muſt premiſe by way of <hi>Theſis:</hi> That the certainty of operation in any Medicine muſt be grounded upon the certain knowledg of the Patient, and a certain knowledg of the Medicine: both which fall ſhort in your appropriation of Medicines; therefore no certainty in
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59336:86"/>ſuch Medicines; at leaſt not ſo certain as a true <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine. Firſt, no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in your peculiar <hi>Appropriate</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine; becauſe this Medicine ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and prepared peculiarly for your Specifical caſe, was never experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monted and tryed; therefore as likely to diſagree, nay more likely then to agree: becauſe variety of compoſition, this with that, ſo far alters every particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient in its vertue and <hi>propriety,</hi> that it is not altogether the ſame in this, as it was before in another compoſition; not can the beſt gueſſer tell what will be the reſult of this new invented Medicine, and conjunction of ingredients; who act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on each other in their aſſociation to alter each others <hi>Proprieties</hi> and ſingle nature, that the <hi>product</hi> Medicine is not to be known but after tryal. Secondly, No certainty of knowledg in the perſon you deſign it for; in as much as no <hi>indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual</hi> and <hi>idio-ſyncratical propriety</hi> is known (in point of agreement and operation of Medicine) farther then the <hi>Specifick</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but preſumed and ſuppoſed at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, untill the tryal of ſuch bodies with that particular Medicine; and then the difference appears.</p>
               <p>Theſe things granted (as true they are)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:59336:86"/>what certainty is there in your <hi>Appropriate</hi> Medicine, particularly appointed for this or that body, before tryal and uſe? what confidence can you have in it? it is but conjecturally deſigned; you never tryed it; it may as likely diſguſt and diſagree with this particular body, as otherwiſe: What is your hopes? You will ſay this for the reaſon of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; That you have tryed all theſe Ingredients, you know them to be ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and agreeable to Nature ſo prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; you have found them to do good in the like caſes, with others; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hope that they will do well in this new compoſition, for this particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Pray what does this differ from the reaſons of a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine that is deſigned to agree with the <hi>Specifick</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man? Your hopes is grounded upon the ſame reaſons and probability, that a <hi>Univerſal</hi> Medicine is; but here is the great difference; the <hi>Catholick</hi> hath been often proved and approved; yours never; becauſe a peculiar new Medicine. Therefore, ſince <hi>Appropriate</hi> Medicines, never tryed, have no more certainty, then a probability of agreement, drawn from the <hi>Specifick</hi> nature of Man, and their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral uſe in other perſons and other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59336:87"/>then you muſt unavoidably allow the Catholick Medicine being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely prepared &amp; gradually perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, frequently tryed and approved; to be more ſafe, certain in operation, and <hi>effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> for its deſigned purpoſe, then any <hi>ex tempore</hi> appropriate unknown medicine.</p>
               <p>And is not there greater hopes in a Catholick Medicine that is known and ſufficiently tryed to operate well and effectually with many in that way of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration it is deſigned; then in a Medicine that was never tryed, and conjecturally contrived to agree with an individual Nature which is occult and unknown? Therefore ſay I, and it is but reaſon; that it is more ſafe to be led and ruled in the deſignment of Medicines, by the Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Nature of Man, then by the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual vnknown propriety: And for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction herein, take a true Catholick known Medicine, and ten peculiar appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Medicines for the ſame operation, never tryed in the perſons for whom they are appointed; and you will finde that the Catholick Medicine (if true and not counterfeit) ſhall better agree, have leſs miſcarriages, and take better effect in the ten ſeveral perſons, then the peculiarly <hi>appropriate</hi> Medicines for each: So that
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:59336:87"/>a good <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine is as well and rationally deſigned for 20. or a hundred perſons, as your ſingle medicine is for one perſon, be as circumſpect as you can, and is as likely, or more likely to do the buſineſs intended: And if you deſire to ſee the experiment of this; preſcribe and prepare you ten <hi>appropriate</hi> Medicines for ten perſons in different caſes or diſeaſes; requiring one and the ſame manner of operation or intention of Cure at that time; whether it be purging, ſweating, ſtrengthening, &amp;c. and I ſhall produce one Catholick Medicine of ſingle opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſame Claſſis; and we will go to tryal whether performes beſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> I can ſpeake by experience that a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Medicine hath failed in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſucceſs; and therefore is not ſo certain a Medicine to effect a Cure as you affirme.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I grant you, the firſt part of your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; but the inference from thence, is not good. I never ſaid that a Catholick medicine is infallibly ſucceſsful in its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: A Catholick Medicine may fail, and may fruſtrate your and my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſometimes; Perhaps one in twenty or forty, may not find the uſuall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected benefit as the reſt receives: but
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59336:88"/>this was the moſt probable Medicine to do it before tryal; this is more certain in operation, this ſeldomer fails then any other: nor is there any Medicine in the world that cures all, or never miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth its wonted ſucceſs. <hi>Optandum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius quam ſperandum tale medicamentum,</hi> ſayes <hi>Sennertus:</hi> ſuch a Medicine may be deſired, but we have no hopes to expect it; if ſuch Medicines were, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence would be reſiſted, Sickneſs would be ſlighted, and Mortality baffled: but there is nothing in nature or art, that alwayes and infallibly can free mortals from their languiſhings and infirmities.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Non eſt in medico ſemper relevetur ut aeger;</l>
                  <l>Interdum docta plus valet arte ma lum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The beſt medicine in the world may fail ſometimes and be fruſtrated of its wonted ſucceſs: and therefore this does not defame or derogate from the <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine; ſince there is no Medicine but does, will and muſt fail ſometimes; but this as ſeldom as any; nay, more certain in operation then any, and more to be relyed on.</p>
               <p>If a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine be the moſt certain,
<note place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> efficacious and beſt Medicine; then where a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine can do no good, there is no hopes in any other
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:59336:88"/>medicine, but the Patient muſt languiſh under his diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>The beſt Medicine in the world may ſail ſometimes;
<note place="margin">Solution.</note> and a more inferiour may do what that could not in ſome particular caſes and bodies. I have known a true <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine to miſs in its common ſucceſs and excellency of operation in ſome one perſon now and then: one in a hundred perhaps ſhall not receive that benefit and advantage which all the reſt have: what is to be done then? Is this perſon to be given over for deſperate? No, I have then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated a Medicine which I thought might better agree with ſuch a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar body; avoiding what I thought might be diſguſting or diſagreeing with that peculiar nature; or ſomething elſe to be added which this ſpecial caſe might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, as the operation of the firſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine hath hinted and dictated to me; and then a much inferiour medicine in point of art, hath done that in ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and complicated diſeaſes, which a more excellent medicine could not effect. And this particular propriety of body, no man can give a ſufficient reaſon for it; nor perhaps well underſtand why the one medicine failed, and why the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:59336:89"/>other had ſucceſs: ſo myſterious and hidden are the operations of nature in their cauſes ſometimes, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is apparent, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> very obſcure and conjectural; and there is no way to find out peculiar different <hi>proprieties</hi> of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in ſuch caſes, but by variation of medicines and rational tryals.</p>
               <p>He that practiſeth with <hi>Catholick</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines of his own preparation is not tyed up to them, that he cannot go far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Cures then they will carry him, nor alter if there be occaſion: he that can rightly deſign and work medicines up to their Catholick operation; knows how to appropriate medicines (if there be occaſion) for any ſpecial caſe and perſon, as well as any man whatever: and if I ſhould ſay better, the aſſertion is rational and eaſie to be proved: for, his experiments are ſo many in his vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tryals of preparation and uſe, before his medicines be Catholick and radical; that he receives more ſatisfaction in the nature and vertues of all medicinal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, then any other, that is but a ſpeculator in medicines, no operator: he ſees and knows their various proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties both genuine and artificial; their diſcord and concord, and <hi>Protean</hi> natures
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:59336:89"/>in ſeveral preparations and vatious aſſociations this with that; which knowledge furniſheth him with variety of medicines for all occaſions whatever; that he is never at a loſs for medicines, and carries a better <hi>Pharmacopoeia</hi> in his head, then another hath in his Library: and he being not only a <hi>Pharmacopaeian</hi> and Operator in medicinal preparations, but alſo a <hi>Compleat Phyſitian;</hi> knows what to aim at in every particular and ſpecial caſe; he can adapt a medicine proper and peculiar (where his <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicines fail) and is as ready at this practice, for contriving and deſigning ſpecial and peculiar Medicines, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch and ſuch <hi>indications,</hi> with as much reaſon and facility, as any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor in this Faculty. He is not like the <hi>Emperick,</hi> that a hath few common Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and can do no more then that ſtock of Medicines he hath pickt up can enable him: the <hi>Compleat Phyſitian</hi> is not limited or tyed to any ſet forms of Medicines, <hi>Catholick</hi> or other; but he is an <hi>ex temporo</hi> man if need be; he can and does vary upon all occaſions neceſſary requiring it: but otherwiſe, he preferrs the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Medicines; in whoſe diſtinct ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations he placeth much confidence, as
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:59336:90"/>moſt ſafe and certain, to make the firſt onſet, and progreſs in their due order, for the <hi>eradicating</hi> of a contumacious diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
                  </label> You ſpeak much in the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicines, but it ſeems ſtrange to me that one Medicine can apply fitly to ſeveral differently diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and of different Conſtitutions; ſome are <hi>Cholerick,</hi> ſome <hi>Phlegmatick,</hi> ſome <hi>Melancholick;</hi> that which is good for one is not good for another, one muſt have a Medicine to purge <hi>Flegme,</hi> another to purge <hi>Choler,</hi> &amp;c. as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of humours abound, and is the cauſe of this or that diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> I grant you there are bodies differing in their ſuperfluous humours and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate matter; lodged here or there, infeſting this or that part, which cauſeth variety of diſeaſes or <hi>ſymptomatical</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances; but notwithſtanding, a good radical medicine carryes all this matter off, be it this or that; not reſpecting the diverſity of its nature: (if it lie within ſpear of its activity; that is if it lie in ſuch a region of the body; where this Medicine diſchargeth its operation,) for, evacuating or purging Medicines do not work <hi>elective</hi> by attracting this or that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:59336:90"/>humour paricularly, as you imagine, and as the world is made to believe: but purgers operate <hi>excitative, fermamentive</hi> and <hi>abſterſive;</hi> by excitation and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of nature to expulſion; by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature upon fermentation and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the pure from the impure; and by ſtmulating <hi>abſterſive properties:</hi> and this is the nature and effect of a true pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Medicine; ſo that there is no particular purger for this or that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; ſome for <hi>Phlegme,</hi> and others for <hi>Melancholy,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Choler;</hi> this is a great miſtake; and thoſe purgets that are ſo accounted and ſuppoſed peculiar attractives; as <hi>Senna, Agarick, Coloquin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tida, Hellebore, Rhubarb, Scammony, &amp;c.</hi> moſt in uſe; are of a <hi>deleterious</hi> and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent</hi> quality, that operate <hi>per modum veneni,</hi> having a <hi>laxative</hi> venome that ſtimulates nature to expulſion; they do not attract this or that humour particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, nor is purgation performed after that manner. From what hath been ſaid, you may reaſonably judge that the <hi>Catholick purgative</hi> medicine is not weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at all, nor limited in its power by this objection; but remains advantagious for variety of bodies, and divers diſeaſes, requiring purgation.</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:59336:91"/>
               <p>The <hi>Emperick</hi> is much pleaſed at this diſcourſe, and thinks it makes well for him and his <hi>Panpharmacum;</hi> and that his practice is as rational as the beſt: but he is much miſtaken; he nor his pretended <hi>Univerſal</hi> Medicine is not concerned here in the leaſt; nor does this diſcourſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ignorant practice and bold pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions of ſuch men; we are ſpeaking of higher things, ſuch as the greateſt <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> and <hi>Phyſitians</hi> have laboured for, and diligently ſought after; nor can any man rightly deſign and endeavour to bring Medicines to <hi>univerſality</hi> of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but he muſt be a <hi>compleat Phyſitian,</hi> a ſolid practiſer and diligent operator in <hi>Medicinal</hi> preparations and tryals; and the practice by <hi>univerſal</hi> Medicines, is the perfection and higheſt pitch that a Phyſitian can attain to: nor are ſuch Medicines attained but by great labour, found knowledg, and much experience. <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicines are ſo far from dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating from the Learned <hi>Doctors;</hi> that they are the perfection and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Medicinal Art:</hi> And we read of ſuch <hi>Arcana's aenigmatically</hi> and darkly diſcovered or diſcourſed of in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the moſt Eminent <hi>Phyſitians Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoeians.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:59336:91"/>
               <p>I remember the Counſel of an able Phyſitian and expert <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> Dr. <hi>Starky,</hi> my acquaintance and friend, who dyed in the laſt Viſitation of the Plague; we diſcourſing how a Phyſitian might fit himſelf compleatly with a ſtock of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines to ſerve his practice upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. His Judgment and Advice was thus much; <hi>That a Phyſitian need not clogg and trouble himſelf with a multitude of ſingle appropriate Medicines for all occaſions; but improve the quality of a few grand Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, diſtinct in operation, and work them to as great a univerſality and large extent of operation as is poſſible; and ſuch will be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable in divers caſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was a man that had uſed and was acquainted with as many Medicines as moſt men in this profeſſion; being a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent labourer in <hi>Chymical Pharmacy,</hi> inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable in various tryals and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: he ſaw the unneceſſary trouble of many medicines; he had but a few in his cuſtody, but thoſe were excellent, and he laboured to improve them in <hi>univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> that they might ſerve in all caſes requiring ſuch an operation. But if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion required, he was not tyed up to theſe, but could vary, and <hi>specificate</hi> his
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:59336:92"/>Medicines for this or that purpoſe, at his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicines which a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian ought principally to labour for are theſe: <hi>Cathartick, Diaphoretick, Diuretick, Anodyne, Bezoardick,</hi> and <hi>Reſtaurative.</hi> The firſt cleanſeth and evacuates by ſtool; the ſecond by or through all the pores of the body; the third by Urine; the fourth mitigates pains, allures the <hi>Archeus</hi> to reſt, and bridles his <hi>exorbitant</hi> motions, which are many and frequent; the fifth reſiſts malignity and venenous aſſaults; the ſixth <hi>roborates</hi> and reſtores the <hi>vital principles.</hi> And theſe are the <hi>grand</hi> and chief <hi>Claſses</hi> of <hi>Medicinal</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, wherein a <hi>compleat Pharmaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poeian</hi> Phyſitian forms his Medicines and Labours by various Experiments and gradual Improvements, that they may be <hi>adequate</hi> and anſwer the full intent of each <hi>Claſſical</hi> diſtinct operation in all Bodies: and ſuch being made <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> are ſtanding. Medicines as Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Stores, from whence a ſolid Phyſitian may deduct and adapt peculiar Medicines (if need be) out of theſe; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming variety of Medicines, <hi>appropriating</hi> them for this or that <hi>ſpecial</hi> Caſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:59336:92"/>ſeveral indications <hi>Cathartick</hi> and <hi>Anodyne; Diuretick</hi> and <hi>Diaphoretick; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uretick</hi> and <hi>Anodine; Diaphoretick</hi> and <hi>Bezoardick; Anodine</hi> and <hi>Diaphoretick; Anodine</hi> and <hi>Bezoardick,</hi> &amp;c. as his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>prore nata</hi> ſhall dictate to him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Compleat Phyſitian</hi> is not tyed up to his Medicines that he cannot alter or vary in his practice; but he is confined to theſe <hi>Claſſes</hi> of operation, which are proper intentions and mediums to effect a Cure by, in a thouſand Diſeaſes: Medicines may be hundreds or thouſands; but the known wayes by which Nature will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive help, are but few; and although your Medicines be never ſo many and various, yet they muſt all be ranked in a few <hi>Claſſes,</hi> they muſt look the ſame way, and have reſpect to the ſame intention and manner of operation: Now where one Medicine can ſatisfie the intention and <hi>ſcope</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Claſsis</hi> of operation, 'tis needleſs and a perplexity to multiply many: <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura, quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is this practice with <hi>Catholick</hi> medicines <hi>Emperical</hi> and <hi>amethodical,</hi> as ſome may fooliſhly ſuppoſe, or others enviouſly ſcandalize; but moſt rationally
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:59336:93"/>founded upon the ſafeſt and beſt rules of Art, having a due regard to neceſſary <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications,</hi> and the requiſite circumſtances of curing. But take notice, he that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth with <hi>radical</hi> medicines need not regard, muſt not obſerve ſo many <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> as is ſet down in the <hi>Methodus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi,</hi> the common <hi>Galenick Method</hi> of curing.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Compleat Phyſitian</hi> in deſigning his medicines, hath his Eye upon the <hi>Specifick</hi> Nature of humane Bodies (not <hi>individual proprieties</hi> which are <hi>occult</hi>), and forms his Medicines according to the fundamental principles of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>in specie,</hi> and the order of deſign of government of each function in Man's Body: And the reaſon why his <hi>indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> for Cure are fewer is, becauſe his medicines are radical, and reſpect the vital and fundamental principles <hi>primò intentionalitèr;</hi> not humors, temperaments, qualities, and the various <hi>Phaenomena's</hi> or <hi>ſymptomes</hi> of Diſeaſes from thence; ſave only <hi>Conſequentèr:</hi> Theſe Medicines apply to the ſprings of Diſeaſes, and Cure <hi>fontalitèr;</hi> they are deſigned, and formed with their faces towards the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> and <hi>fundamental</hi> principles of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:59336:93"/>from whence as theſe are affected and according to the ſtate and condition they are in, whether in fortitude, debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or declenſion; in rectitude or devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; humors, <hi>temperaments</hi> and qualities vary and alter; and divers ſymptomes from thence appear in ſeveral parts of the body, and again diſappear; being the reſult and <hi>products</hi> depending upon the former in generation and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And therefore he that manageth theſe <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicines, which cure <hi>à priori et in radice;</hi> regards not the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of ſymptomatical and various productions in ſeverall parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; farther then as <hi>Characters</hi> and marks to know where and how the principles of our Nature ſwerve from integrity: ſuch fall of courſe, and are cut down by the ſtroake of a <hi>Radicall</hi> Medicine, as many branches depending upon one toot.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Galenick appropriate</hi> Medicines which apply <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> to theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts and <hi>ſymptomatical</hi> appearances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing various, they alſo muſt be many and divers; and yet but <hi>Palliative</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain; they lop off, but not eradicate; they may carry off and abate ſomething
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:59336:94"/>of the producted vitious matter; but the diſeaſe remains behind in the principles of nature untoucht, that generates, <hi>de novo</hi> the like matter, or ſomething worſe. The Axiom is true; <hi>natura eſt morborum medicatrix:</hi> 'tis nature that cures; and you muſt apply to nature; how is that? to aſſiſt the <hi>vital principles,</hi> to ſet all things right there; the reſt follows of courſe; humours and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments and qualities depend here, have their ſubſiſtance from hence. You muſt not object the diverſity of Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions (as you call them) againſt <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> medicines; that apply <hi>à priori</hi> to the <hi>fundamentals,</hi> to the ſprings of diſeaſes; becauſe <hi>Galenick, Appropriate</hi> medicines that apply <hi>à posteriori</hi> to humours and qualities are bound to obſerve theſe diſtinctions and many <hi>indications</hi> which the other <hi>radical</hi> medicines has no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to. He that cures <hi>radically,</hi> does not regard humours; but the humour of the <hi>Archaeus</hi> which is <hi>dominus vitae</hi> he well obſerves, and takes notice what humour and mood he is in; whether brisk and chearful, or melancholy; whether vigorous and ſtrong, or labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weak and declining; whether in a
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:59336:94"/>ſtate of <hi>rectitude</hi> in the government of all the functions, or <hi>extravagant</hi> and <hi>enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid we may rationally conclude; that to contract the practice of Phyſick, into certain <hi>Claſſes</hi> of operation, with ſome excellent <hi>radical</hi> medicine <hi>adapted</hi> thereto is the <hi>compleat</hi> practice of Phyſick and well becomes the greateſt Doctor in this <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty:</hi> and he that hath purchaſed <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> medicines in theſe ſeveral <hi>Claſses</hi> of operation by his own deſign, labour and experiments (which preſuppoſeth and neceſſarily comprehends all other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments of a Phyſitian) is bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed upon his own reaſon and certain experiments, is not over-ruled by any Authority but is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; hath the whole deſign and myſtery of Phyſick in his head; is a rule to himſelf, a Maſter of this Art, and a <hi>Compleat Phyſitian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might have enlarged my ſelf much more upon this ſubject, but I muſt draw to a concluſion, and ſumme up the whole of this diſcourſe in theſe following <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That ſince ſpecificks are rare,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">Corollary.</note> obſcure and difficult to know, the <hi>Catholick</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:59336:95"/>are beſt to rely on, and will do a Phyſitian the greateſt ſervice in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of his practice.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By how much Medicines are more Catholick and Univerſall in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Claſses</hi> of operation, by ſo much the more noble and of excelling ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicines of manifeſt operation, are moſt certain and ſafe: for, having undergone ſo many tryals of preparation and uſe to give them their latitude and perfection; are Medicines ſo proved and approved, that we may confide in and expect much, from former experiences and ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> That no <hi>conjectural appropriate</hi> medicine before tryall, hath that probability of ſucceſs and certainty of operation as a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> That the probability and reaſon of your hopes in an <hi>Appropriate</hi> or <hi>Specifick</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to work a good effect in this or that ſpecial Caſe; is drawn from the <hi>Analogy</hi> of former Experiments, and the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:59336:95"/>
                  <hi>Catholick</hi> Vertues of the Ingredients ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in like manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That a <hi>Catholick Medicine</hi> of known Vertue and Worth, excellent in that operation it is intended and deſigned for; is the ſafeſt and moſt hopeful Medicine in any Diſeaſe where ſuch an operation is required.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That the variation of medicines this with that, and <hi>adapting</hi> of them to pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar caſes; is but by way of probation, not any certainty above a Catholick untill tryal; and may as likely diſguſt as agree.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> That a true <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Radical</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is as rationally and according to the trueſt Rules of <hi>Medical Art,</hi> deſigned to operate as amicably, ſafely and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully with an hundred ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and caſes (requiring ſuch an opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) as an <hi>appropriate</hi> medicine is for one perſon and caſe.</p>
               <p>That humors,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> temperaments and firſt qualities, do not <hi>indicate</hi> variation of Medicines; but the different <hi>propriety</hi> of
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:59336:96"/>
                  <hi>individual</hi> and <hi>fundamental</hi> principles, forceth a Phyſitian to alteration and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Medicines.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> That a <hi>Catholick</hi> Medicine not having its wonted and uſual operation in ſome particular perſon of difficult and diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>propriety</hi> of body; requires ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration to make it more congruous, or another medicine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> That Catholick Medicines manifeſt more the Excellency of Art; Specificks the work of Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:59336:96"/>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>I Intended one Tract more to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this Work; in anſwer to a pernicious Poſition and irrational Tenent (lately in print): namely, that it is for the good of Man-kind there ſhould be a liberty allowed in the Profeſſion of Phyſick.</p>
               <p>And this is carried on under a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence of advancing and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging the Art: whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, by ſuch a ſtrange Proſtitution, we ſhould have ſuch a monſtrous Brood of Illiterate Practiſers ſpawned by this Adulteration; that in a ſhort time, by this diſcountenance and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Learning; by their prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Inſolencies and upbraiding men of the Gown; The whole Profeſſion would fall into the Captivity of rude Mechanick Invaders.</p>
               <p>And this moſt Learned Art, wither
<pb facs="tcp:59336:97"/>away and periſh in the hands of illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate and unskilfull men, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Nation, and great prejudice to all people.</p>
               <p>But I am prevented at preſent, by intervening occaſions; that I cannot diſcuſs this matter as it ought, and lay open the evil conſequents that would attend it; but muſt wait the next op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for a proſecution.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:97"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for the Book-ſellers of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOrbus Polyrhizos &amp; Polymor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaeus</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Treatiſe of the Scurvy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Examining opinions and errors concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature and cure of this Diſeaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſcribing</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A due courſe for Prevention and Cure: The third Edition, with Practical Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</hi> By Dr. <hi>Mainwaringe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Conſumptions
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Scorbutick Atrophies</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tabes Anglica</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hectick Feavers</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phthiſick</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spermatick and venereous wasting.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Radically demonstrating their Nature and Cures from vital and morbifick cauſes. The ſecond Edition, by the ſame Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:98"/>
            <p>Tutela Sanitatis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The protection of long life, and detection of its brevity from diaetetick cauſes and customs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Diſcourſe of Fontinels or Iſsues. By the ſame Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solamen Aegrorum Sive</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ternarius Medicamentorum Chymico rum, ad omnes fere morbos curan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum (<hi>Galenica</hi> remedia <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> eludentes) faeliciſſimè inventa Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Studio &amp; operà ejuſdem Authoris.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:59336:98"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe remarkable errors of the Preſs the Reader is deſired more eſpecially to take notice of.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>In page 6. of the Epiſt. Dedicat. l. 23. Read <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page 6. Epiſt. to the Reader, l. 1. utut.</item>
               <item>Page 44. l. 3. Proceſs.</item>
               <item>Page 35. l. 16. operators.</item>
               <item>Page 54. l. 2. lawful.</item>
               <item>Page 80. l. 14. priſtine vigour.</item>
               <item>Page 91. from l. 4. to l. 14. ſhould be in ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man letters.</item>
               <item>☞ Page 114. from l. 22. the Comma's down the ſide ſhould be out.</item>
               <item>Page 138, l. 18. ſome other.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
